<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>RSE Asia Association</title><link>https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/</link><atom:link href="https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>RSE Asia Association</description><generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 24 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/media/icon_hu11734318148517933569.png</url><title>RSE Asia Association</title><link>https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/</link></image><item><title>RSE Asia signs its first MoU</title><link>https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-08-04-apan_mou/</link><pubDate>Tue, 02 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-08-04-apan_mou/</guid><description>&lt;p>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="Image: RSE Asia and APAN signing the MoU." srcset="
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-08-04-apan_mou/RSE_Asia_APAN_MoU_hu432188780849466740.webp 400w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-08-04-apan_mou/RSE_Asia_APAN_MoU_hu16565271671934022273.webp 760w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-08-04-apan_mou/RSE_Asia_APAN_MoU_hu9339817199177199870.webp 1200w"
src="https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-08-04-apan_mou/RSE_Asia_APAN_MoU_hu432188780849466740.webp"
width="760"
height="760"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/p>
&lt;p>At the 60th meeting of the &lt;a href="https://apan60.apan.net/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Asia Pacific Advanced Network (APAN60)&lt;/a> in Hong Kong, the RSE Asia Association officially signed its first-ever Memorandum of Understanding (MoU) with the &lt;a href="https://apan.net/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Asia Pacific Advanced Network (APAN)&lt;/a>. At the signing, the RSE Asia Association was represented by our Co-Founder Jyoti Bhogal and the Asia Pacific Advanced Network was represented by the Chair of the APAN Board of Directors, Prof. Dr. Shinji Shimojo.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="what-is-apan">What is APAN?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The Asia Pacific Advanced Network (APAN) is the international partnership of the National Research and Education Networks NRENs connecting communities across the Asia-Pacific region. APAN provides a platform for collaboration, knowledge sharing, and the development of advanced networking technologies to support research and education.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="what-does-this-mou-mean-for-rse-asia">What does this MoU mean for RSE Asia?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>This collaboration marks an exciting step forward for our volunteer-driven community, committed to raising awareness and building capacity in research software engineering (RSE) across Asia. With APAN’s extensive network of research and education stakeholders primarily focused around the Asia-Pacific and RSE Asia’s growing grassroots community, this collaboration opens up new opportunities to support researchers and software engineers alike within the region.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="next-steps">Next steps&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The MoU outlines several key areas of collaboration between RSE Asia and APAN. We’re excited to begin this journey together and look forward to co-developing initiatives that benefit the research software engineering community in Asia!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>To stay updated on what’s next, follow our &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/company/rse-asia-association/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">LinkedIn page&lt;/a>!&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h3 id="learn-more-about-us">&lt;strong>Learn More About Us&lt;/strong>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>For more information and to join upcoming events, visit:&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="rse-asia">RSE Asia&lt;/h4>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Website: &lt;a href="https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>For the latest news, events, activities, and opportunities, follow us on our &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/company/rse-asia-association/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">LinkedIn page&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>To join the RSE Asia community, please fill out our short &lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/forms/d/1XSxDaTJzcNyGeDYXyJNVg1TDCo7un18PLFNiK6_jL2g/edit" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Community Membership Form&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul></description></item><item><title>RSE Asia signs its first MoU with Asia Pacific Advanced Network (APAN)</title><link>https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/post/30-07-25-mou-apan/</link><pubDate>Wed, 30 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/post/30-07-25-mou-apan/</guid><description>&lt;p>RSE Asia signs its first MoU with Asia Pacific Advanced Network (APAN) to promote Research Software Engineering (RSE) in the Asia-Pacific region.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>RSE Asia is proud to announce the signing of its first Memorandum of Understanding (MoU) with the Asia Pacific Advanced Network (APAN). This partnership marks a significant milestone in our mission to promote and support Research Software Engineering (RSE) across the Asia-Pacific region.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Halò Scotland! Visiting EPCC in the Edinburgh Sunshine</title><link>https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-05-27_epcc_talk/</link><pubDate>Thu, 29 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-05-27_epcc_talk/</guid><description>&lt;p>As part of my SSI Fellowship project, I was invited to visit &lt;a href="https://www.epcc.ed.ac.uk/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">EPCC at the University of Edinburgh&lt;/a> and give a talk about my work. This was following my participation in the &lt;a href="https://www.software.ac.uk/workshop/collaborations-workshop-2025-cw25" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Collaborations Workshop 2025&lt;/a> organised by the &lt;a href="https://www.software.ac.uk/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Software Sustainability Institute (SSI)&lt;/a> at the &lt;a href="https://www.stir.ac.uk/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">University of Stirling&lt;/a>. I was joined by SSI Fellows &lt;strong>Samantha Wittke&lt;/strong> and &lt;strong>Saranjeet Kaur&lt;/strong>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="Image: (Left to Right) SSI Fellows: Saranjeet Kaur, Jyoti Bhogal, Samantha Wittke at EPCC, Bayes Center, University of Edinburgh against the backdrop of the Holyrood Park (Salisbury Crags on the left, Arthur’s Seat on the right). Image credit: Catherine Inglis." srcset="
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-05-27_epcc_talk/bayes_center_holyrood_park_hu6226188194357269549.webp 400w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-05-27_epcc_talk/bayes_center_holyrood_park_hu5920640209434281563.webp 760w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-05-27_epcc_talk/bayes_center_holyrood_park_hu13504879025344997513.webp 1200w"
src="https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-05-27_epcc_talk/bayes_center_holyrood_park_hu6226188194357269549.webp"
width="760"
height="351"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/p>
&lt;p>On the day, &lt;strong>Catherine Inglis&lt;/strong> and &lt;strong>Neil Chue Hong&lt;/strong> welcomed us to the &lt;a href="https://bayes-centre.ed.ac.uk/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Bayes Centre at EPCC&lt;/a>. The robots on the ground floor of the Bayes Centre are hard to miss, and I must say, I was captivated by them! We all went on a tour of the EPCC building and met several members of the team there. Later, we stepped out and had a lunch break in the beautiful and sunny campus of the University of Edinburgh. It was during the chats with Catherine and Neil, I got to know that the Unicorn 🦄 - an imaginary creature - is the National Animal of Scotland, and then it made sense to me why the buildings in Edinburgh have so many unicorn statues!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="Image: (Left to Right) A robot at the Bayes Center, University of Edinburgh; The Unicron, the National Animal of Scotland" srcset="
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-05-27_epcc_talk/robot_unicorn_hu14053791878051609495.webp 400w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-05-27_epcc_talk/robot_unicorn_hu1885357626098156738.webp 760w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-05-27_epcc_talk/robot_unicorn_hu2764780780526347097.webp 1200w"
src="https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-05-27_epcc_talk/robot_unicorn_hu14053791878051609495.webp"
width="760"
height="562"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/p>
&lt;p>There were two talks planned for the day. The first one was by Samantha, who shared about the &lt;a href="https://coderefinery.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">CodeRefinery&lt;/a> project and her work with the &lt;a href="https://nordic-rse.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Nordic RSE&lt;/a>. Later, I presented my talk on the ongoing ‘Research Study on the Research Software Engineering (RSEng) Landscape in Asia’. Coincidentally, there were a few common points touched during both the talks - maybe CodeRefinery and RSE Asia could collaborate more closely in the future, but for now, I will focus this blog on my talk! 😊&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="Image: Jyoti Bhogal speaking about her “Research Study on the Research Software Engineering (RSEng) Landscape in Asia” at EPCC, Bayes Center, University of Edinburgh." srcset="
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-05-27_epcc_talk/epcc_jyoti_talk_title_slide_hu13862556047850879380.webp 400w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-05-27_epcc_talk/epcc_jyoti_talk_title_slide_hu18395822772695636408.webp 760w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-05-27_epcc_talk/epcc_jyoti_talk_title_slide_hu9049008084742139433.webp 1200w"
src="https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-05-27_epcc_talk/epcc_jyoti_talk_title_slide_hu13862556047850879380.webp"
width="760"
height="493"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="what-is-rse-asia">What is RSE Asia?&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>We (I and my co-Founder &lt;strong>Saranjeet Kaur&lt;/strong>) launched the &lt;a href="https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Research Software Engineering Asia Association (RSE Asia)&lt;/a> back in 2021, on the &lt;a href="https://researchsoftware.org/council/intl-rse-day.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">very first International RSE Day&lt;/a>, as there was almost no awareness about Research Software Engineering in the Asian region. Over the past 3+ years we have conducted and participated in various events and workshops to raise awareness about the profession and the community. Based on the reflections over this period, I started to explore the RSE landscape in the Asian region to get better informed insights.&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="what-is-my-project-about">What is my project about?&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>The motivation for this project was gained after reflecting over several of the community initiatives and interactions that RSE Asia had with the community in the region. I was further encouraged to take this work ahead when I proposed the idea during my talk on ‘&lt;a href="https://jyoti-bhogal.github.io/about-me/talks/2025-03-30_apan58/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">What is Research Software and Why Should we Think About its Sustainability?&lt;/a>’ at the 58th meeting of the Asia Pacific Advanced Network (APAN58) during August 2024, which was attended by delegates from across Asia Pacific as well as the globe. I have been developing this idea since then, and have been encouraged and supported to do so by several RSE community members, SSI fellows, and community leaders.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Speaking of why this study is required - this study is essential for several reasons, some of which are the need to diversify and expand the research software landscape, attempt to address the lack of formal RSE roles in Asia, leverage international partnerships, and further build a supportive community within Asia.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>SSI has been conducting surveys to study the RSE landscape since 2018. However, there has been almost no representation of Asia in these surveys. This makes my research study even more essential.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="Image: RSEs in the world in 2018, originally shared in the blog What do we know about RSEs? Results from our international surveys." srcset="
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-05-27_epcc_talk/ssi_survery_map_hu15950245902033643575.webp 400w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-05-27_epcc_talk/ssi_survery_map_hu11096678663734903656.webp 760w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-05-27_epcc_talk/ssi_survery_map_hu672506643558864757.webp 1200w"
src="https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-05-27_epcc_talk/ssi_survery_map_hu15950245902033643575.webp"
width="760"
height="375"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Within Asia, the Asia-Pacific Advanced Network (APAN) is an organisation that represents member institutions as well as it is a backbone network connecting member countries and regions to each other and to other international research and education networks. I am a member of APAN’s &lt;a href="https://apan.net/elements/working-groups/open-sharing-data/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Open and Sharing Data Working Group (OSDWG)&lt;/a>. This working group engages in dialogue and activities to promote good open science practices within research roles/institutes in the Asia Pacific. RSE Asia has had a consistent voice and representation during the biannual APAN meetings as a part of this working group. Through these engagements we realised the common interests we share with the working group and their intentions to help support the objectives of RSE Asia. Asia being a very complex and diverse region both, culturally and economically, it is essential to have the support from an established working group like the APAN’s OSDWG so as to have a better understanding of the research software landscape in the region.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="Image: APAN Current Members (as of December 2024). Source of information for creating map: APAN website." srcset="
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-05-27_epcc_talk/apan_current_members_hu16407296222288056876.webp 400w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-05-27_epcc_talk/apan_current_members_hu4347439335617471336.webp 760w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-05-27_epcc_talk/apan_current_members_hu4429776868388002966.webp 1200w"
src="https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-05-27_epcc_talk/apan_current_members_hu16407296222288056876.webp"
width="760"
height="485"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/p>
&lt;p>So far in this project, I have been able to refine and adapt the existing SSI surveys to make them suitable for the Asian context. I have also launched a pilot survey with a small group in APAN’s OSDWG to gain first-hand feedback on the survey so far. Next, I plan to refine the survey further based on this feedback before launching the full survey to a larger group. If you are either a researcher based in Asia or have worked in the Asian region or collaborate with colleagues in Asia, then please watch the &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/company/rse-asia-association/?viewAsMember=true" target="_blank" rel="noopener">RSE Asia page&lt;/a> for updates about my project and the survey - I would love to hear from you!&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="-concluding-the-day">🎉 Concluding the day&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>After the talks, we spent some time discussing our work with the audience, which smoothly transitioned into EPCC’s ritual of ‘Friday Buns’. We discussed the challenges and way forward. Later that evening, I walked up the Calton hill (recommended by many) and got to see a 360° view of the city, the valleys, as well as the beautiful North Sea. Being a bright, sunny day, with the sun setting almost post 10 pm, I went for a walk to the Portobello Beach, and loved every bit of it!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="Image (Left to Right): Me against the backdrop of the National Monument of Scotland on the Calton Hill; The beautiful blues and browns of the Portobello Beach in Edinburgh." srcset="
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-05-27_epcc_talk/edinburgh_nature_hu3289953717683451112.webp 400w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-05-27_epcc_talk/edinburgh_nature_hu18377849314722569752.webp 760w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-05-27_epcc_talk/edinburgh_nature_hu14326735887658741747.webp 1200w"
src="https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-05-27_epcc_talk/edinburgh_nature_hu3289953717683451112.webp"
width="760"
height="365"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I sincerely want to thank &lt;strong>Neil Chue Hong&lt;/strong> for inviting me to EPCC and to &lt;strong>Catherine Inglis&lt;/strong> for all the hospitality she offered. Last but definitely not least, a big thanks to &lt;strong>Sohail Sukhiani&lt;/strong> and &lt;strong>Oscar Seip&lt;/strong> for offering me a lot of behind-the-scenes support. I immensely value this opportunity of personal and professional growth!&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="-resources">🔑 Resources:&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Talk slides:&lt;/strong> &lt;a href="https://zenodo.org/records/15450346" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://zenodo.org/records/15450346&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h3 id="learn-more-about-us">&lt;strong>Learn More About Us&lt;/strong>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>For more information and to join upcoming events, visit:&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="rse-asia">RSE Asia&lt;/h4>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Website: &lt;a href="https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>For the latest news, events, activities, and opportunities, follow us on our &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/company/rse-asia-association/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">LinkedIn page&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>To join the RSE Asia community, please fill out our short &lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/forms/d/1XSxDaTJzcNyGeDYXyJNVg1TDCo7un18PLFNiK6_jL2g/edit" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Community Membership Form&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul></description></item><item><title>FOSSASIA Summit 2025</title><link>https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/</link><pubDate>Thu, 10 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/</guid><description>&lt;p>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="Wat Arun Ratchawararam Ratchawaramahawihan (Wat Arun temple), Bangkok, Thailand." srcset="
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/preview_wat_arun_hu4395619707160518832.webp 400w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/preview_wat_arun_hu12870335760176420076.webp 760w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/preview_wat_arun_hu4883880939432868856.webp 1200w"
src="https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/preview_wat_arun_hu4395619707160518832.webp"
width="760"
height="407"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>&lt;strong>Swa-dee-kah Bangkok! 👋🙏&lt;/strong>&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="-what-is-foss">🧑‍💻 What is FOSS?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>FOSS, an acronym for Free and Open Source Software, embodies a software development philosophy centered on freedom and openness. The term &amp;lsquo;Free&amp;rsquo; denotes users&amp;rsquo; liberty to run, alter, and share the software, while &amp;lsquo;Open Source&amp;rsquo; signifies that the software&amp;rsquo;s source code is available for users to inspect, modify, and contribute to its progress. FOSS promotes collaboration, transparency, and user empowerment. This frequently leads to the creation of more secure and sustainable software projects. Notable examples of FOSS include Linux, Blender, Chromium, Kubernetes, and Mozilla Firefox, among many more.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="-what-is-fossasia">🧑‍💻🌏 What is FOSSASIA?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://fossasia.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">FOSSASIA&lt;/a> is an organisation developing Open Source software applications and Open Hardware together with a global community from its base in Asia. Their goal is to provide access to open technologies, science applications and knowledge that improve people&amp;rsquo;s lives. They enable people to adapt and change technology according to their own ideas and needs, and validate science and knowledge through an Open Access approach. It was established in 2009 by &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/hongphucdang/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Hong Phuc Dang&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/mariobehling/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Mario Behling&lt;/a>. They organise and participate in conferences, meetups and code camps. The annual FOSSASIA Summit is one of the top tech events in Asia. FOSSASIA also runs a number of coding programs, such as &lt;a href="https://codeheat.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Codeheat&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The &lt;a href="https://eventyay.com/e/4c0e0c27" target="_blank" rel="noopener">15th edition of FOSSASIA Summit&lt;/a> was organised at True Digital Park, Bangkok, Thailand from 13th to 15th March 2025. It brought together individuals sharing talks on topics around Free and Open Source Software. The Summit had multiple parallel track sessions like talks, lightning talks, workshops, and more! There were booths by various organisations creating and/or using Free and Open Source Software. This was my first experience of attending FOSSASIA in-person in Thailand.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="-day-1">🗓️ Day 1&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The day started with a lot of fervour. Following the welcome session by Hong Phuc Dang, there were multiple parallel tracks of talks. One of the booths demonstrated &lt;em>&lt;strong>Robot Jupiter&lt;/strong>&lt;/em> (image below) - an interactive virtual education assistant!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="Robot Jupiter, virtual education assistant" srcset="
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/jupiter_robot_educational_assistant_hu13794346810542124047.webp 400w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/jupiter_robot_educational_assistant_hu596505261004575245.webp 760w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/jupiter_robot_educational_assistant_hu10152196276004389370.webp 1200w"
src="https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/jupiter_robot_educational_assistant_hu13794346810542124047.webp"
width="553"
height="760"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I had a chance to speak to Nancy Reyes, a representative from the &lt;a href="https://www.a11ylab.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">A11y Accessibility Labs&lt;/a>. She was showcasing the hardware items that they use for digital accessibility awareness training during their Usability and Accessibility Clinic sessions.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="Hardware items for digital accessibility awareness training" srcset="
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/hardware_and_software_accessibility_hu2981789961161384236.webp 400w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/hardware_and_software_accessibility_hu9049655007414283981.webp 760w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/hardware_and_software_accessibility_hu7704078689759508196.webp 1200w"
src="https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/hardware_and_software_accessibility_hu2981789961161384236.webp"
width="760"
height="365"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="A picture with Nancy Reyes from the A11y Accessibility Labs" srcset="
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/rse_asia_hu18357443411752010818.webp 400w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/rse_asia_hu6255961377230065161.webp 760w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/rse_asia_hu764290853054273577.webp 1200w"
src="https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/rse_asia_hu18357443411752010818.webp"
width="288"
height="216"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;em>A picture with &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/nancyreyesfl/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Nancy Reyes&lt;/a>, from the &lt;a href="https://www.a11ylab.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">A11y Accessibility Labs&lt;/a>, speaking about the mission of the RSE Asia Association.&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="-day-2">🗓️ Day 2&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="Me against the backdrop of the live LED screens at the conference venue True Digital Park." srcset="
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/jyoti_bhogal_true_digital_park_hu9211724051775702194.webp 400w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/jyoti_bhogal_true_digital_park_hu6454441547086564381.webp 760w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/jyoti_bhogal_true_digital_park_hu6852337217411483051.webp 1200w"
src="https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/jyoti_bhogal_true_digital_park_hu9211724051775702194.webp"
width="570"
height="760"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The second day of the summit, 14th March, was themed as PGDay 2025, a 1-day event focused on the PostgreSQL database, which was held in conjunction with the FOSSASIA Summit. I learnt about a new tool - &lt;a href="https://pgroll.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">pgroll&lt;/a>. It is an open-source command-line tool designed for PostgreSQL, ensuring that schema updates are applied safely, without locking the database, and enabling multiple schema versions to coexist. This ensures uninterrupted operation for client applications during migration, even when introducing breaking changes. The tool’s capability to automatically backfill columns and support instant rollbacks further enhances its reliability.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Later that day, I came across the booth of &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/company/grafana-labs/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Grafana Labs&lt;/a>. As I spoke to &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/richih/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Richard Hartmann&lt;/a>, he shared about the useful features of Grafana Labs tools for creating reports, metrics, and graphs about the code being written.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="-day-3">🗓️ Day 3&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>I held a ‘&lt;em>&lt;strong>Meet &amp;amp; Greet Spot&lt;/strong>&lt;/em>’ to speak to people about the field of Research Software Engineering, and discussed how it is a career path where one can combine their interest in implementing their research skills along with programming skills. I also shared about the past and the upcoming activities of the &lt;a href="https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Research Software Engineering (RSE) Asia Association&lt;/a>. Most people were curious to learn more about it, and also expressed a desire to join the future events held for the community.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="At the conference venue entrance door" srcset="
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/jyoti_bhogal_fossasia_summit_2025_poster_hu11164068731775730425.webp 400w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/jyoti_bhogal_fossasia_summit_2025_poster_hu17398043740992248417.webp 760w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/jyoti_bhogal_fossasia_summit_2025_poster_hu6485354994626380674.webp 1200w"
src="https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/jyoti_bhogal_fossasia_summit_2025_poster_hu11164068731775730425.webp"
width="760"
height="570"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="-cultural-warmth">👥 Cultural Warmth&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>From the moment I arrived at the Suvarnabhumi airport, I found everyone to be warm and welcoming. People at help desks, metro ticket counters, and even local markets were kind and helped me get around the city easily. I also learned something new about Thailand — it&amp;rsquo;s a pedestrian-first country, where vehicles stop to let people cross the road. Another thing I noticed was a good gender balance in the different workplaces that I came across.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="Depiction of Samudra Manthan (The Churning of the Ocean Milk), Suvarnabhumi Airport" srcset="
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/churning_ocean_milk_suvarnabhumi_airport_hu4853565785052944587.webp 400w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/churning_ocean_milk_suvarnabhumi_airport_hu6168598445551651087.webp 760w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/churning_ocean_milk_suvarnabhumi_airport_hu11578171994200421043.webp 1200w"
src="https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/churning_ocean_milk_suvarnabhumi_airport_hu4853565785052944587.webp"
width="760"
height="570"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/p>
&lt;p>With fresh fruits like mangoes, jackfruits, bananas, guavas, cashews, and coconuts, I truly experienced the tropical feel of the country. I enjoyed trying different types of bread, like red bean and almond bread. I also got to taste authentic Pad Thai noodles and Veg Thai Curry at a restaurant in True Digital Park. A fellow participant at the conference even taught me how to use chopsticks practically. I found Bangkok’s infrastructure very supportive for growth, with great workspaces and plenty of learning resources to help you make your own impact. Everyone I met — from the conference team to the hotel staff — was friendly and helpful, making the city feel not just a hub to flourish businesses and communities, but a place that warmly welcomes you again and again.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Here’s a glimpse of Bangkok through my eyes!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="Pad Thai noodles and vegetarian Thai curry at the Ginger Farm restaurant, True Digital Park" srcset="
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/pad_thai_noodles_hu255893316726781715.webp 400w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/pad_thai_noodles_hu3977903085000017417.webp 760w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/pad_thai_noodles_hu14899025521790407705.webp 1200w"
src="https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/pad_thai_noodles_hu255893316726781715.webp"
width="760"
height="570"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="The Great Bodhi Tree at the Wat Arun Ratchawararam Ratchawaramahawihan (Wat Arun temple), Bangkok, Thailand" srcset="
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/wat_arun_bodhi_tree_hu15311312930013773606.webp 400w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/wat_arun_bodhi_tree_hu5216849017775580175.webp 760w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/wat_arun_bodhi_tree_hu9074338275543790205.webp 1200w"
src="https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/wat_arun_bodhi_tree_hu15311312930013773606.webp"
width="760"
height="570"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="Night view of the Wat Arun Ratchawararam Ratchawaramahawihan (Wat Arun temple), Bangkok, Thailand" srcset="
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/wat_arun_night_view_hu17000656014442621381.webp 400w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/wat_arun_night_view_hu10811269505631675359.webp 760w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/wat_arun_night_view_hu11174394000620591023.webp 1200w"
src="https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/wat_arun_night_view_hu17000656014442621381.webp"
width="760"
height="570"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="Wat Pho, also known as the Temple of the Reclining Buddha" srcset="
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/wat_pho_temple_2_hu7248716128776745831.webp 400w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/wat_pho_temple_2_hu6475442039930818039.webp 760w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/wat_pho_temple_2_hu6707752146234198869.webp 1200w"
src="https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/wat_pho_temple_2_hu7248716128776745831.webp"
width="760"
height="570"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="Wat Pho, also known as the Temple of the Reclining Buddha" srcset="
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/wat_pho_temple_3_hu5642525036103178549.webp 400w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/wat_pho_temple_3_hu4898327453772873588.webp 760w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/wat_pho_temple_3_hu7697316060564706644.webp 1200w"
src="https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/wat_pho_temple_3_hu5642525036103178549.webp"
width="760"
height="570"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="-my-takeaway-">📕 My takeaway …&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>FOSSASIA Summit 2025 was especially close to my heart because it rekindled in me the spirit, zeal, and dedication towards contributing back to the software that we, knowingly or unknowingly, use on a day-to-day basis. As I left Thailand to return home, I carried so many learnings with me - especially the power that the voice of a community has!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>With that, I am concluding this blog until next time …&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="Wat Pho, also known as the Temple of the Reclining Buddha" srcset="
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/wat_pho_temple_1_hu7358190283318141940.webp 400w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/wat_pho_temple_1_hu6465378563647337677.webp 760w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/wat_pho_temple_1_hu12817486395345895593.webp 1200w"
src="https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/wat_pho_temple_1_hu7358190283318141940.webp"
width="760"
height="570"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h3 id="learn-more-about-us">&lt;strong>Learn More About Us&lt;/strong>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>For more information and to join upcoming events, visit:&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="rse-asia">RSE Asia&lt;/h4>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Website: &lt;a href="https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>For the latest news, events, activities, and opportunities, follow us on our &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/company/rse-asia-association/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">LinkedIn page&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>To join the RSE Asia community, please fill out our short &lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/forms/d/1XSxDaTJzcNyGeDYXyJNVg1TDCo7un18PLFNiK6_jL2g/edit" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Community Membership Form&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul></description></item><item><title>Research, Software, and Collaborations</title><link>https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-03-30_apan58_apan59_blog/</link><pubDate>Thu, 10 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-03-30_apan58_apan59_blog/</guid><description>&lt;p>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="Mount Fuji, Japan. Photo by David Edelstein on Unsplash" srcset="
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-03-30_apan58_apan59_blog/david-edelstein-N4DbvTUDikw-unsplash_hu18157301937796507309.webp 400w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-03-30_apan58_apan59_blog/david-edelstein-N4DbvTUDikw-unsplash_hu2469300309647533437.webp 760w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-03-30_apan58_apan59_blog/david-edelstein-N4DbvTUDikw-unsplash_hu9811291813246369947.webp 1200w"
src="https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-03-30_apan58_apan59_blog/david-edelstein-N4DbvTUDikw-unsplash_hu18157301937796507309.webp"
width="580"
height="388"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>What is the Asia-Pacific Advanced Network (APAN)?&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>APAN is the international partnership of the National Research and Education Networks (NRENs) across the Asia Pacific region. It spans over half of the world’s population, and its members are fundamental in the provision of high-speed network connectivity domestically and globally.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>APAN has a number of working groups, one of which is the Open and Sharing Data Working Group (OSDWG). I became a member of this working group based on the common interest around developing the research software community and its importance in the research ecosystem.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>APAN organises biannual meetings bringing together its members and other interested participants to review progress, demonstrate advances in technology and applications, and make plans for the future activities in the Asia Pacific. Over the past months, I got the chance to attend APAN58 and APAN59 meetings, online remotely and exchange knowledge with its stakeholders. In this blog, I am capturing my experiences of attending these meetings.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="APAN58 Presentation Image" srcset="
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-03-30_apan58_apan59_blog/APAN58_talk_image_1_software_sustainability_methods_hu12679255357699436917.webp 400w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-03-30_apan58_apan59_blog/APAN58_talk_image_1_software_sustainability_methods_hu1880345936431998876.webp 760w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-03-30_apan58_apan59_blog/APAN58_talk_image_1_software_sustainability_methods_hu2976238838862877632.webp 1200w"
src="https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-03-30_apan58_apan59_blog/APAN58_talk_image_1_software_sustainability_methods_hu12679255357699436917.webp"
width="760"
height="347"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Source:&lt;/em> &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=giTd8lN88KQ" target="_blank" rel="noopener">APAN58 : Asia Pacific Open and Sharing Data WG, 27th August 2024, Part 1&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>During the APAN58 meeting (August 2024), I had the opportunity to present my talk titled &lt;em>&lt;strong>‘What is Research Software and Why Should we Think About its Sustainability?’&lt;/strong>&lt;/em> as part of the Open and Sharing Data Working Group (OSDWG) discussion session. Through my talk, I highlighted the importance of Research Software in the research ecosystem, explaining why it is necessary to think about its sustainability. I shared methods, tools, and best practices that can be utilised to improve the sustainability of research software, following up with the need and the benefits to include techniques for reproducibility in Research Software. Furthermore, I shared what software tools can be used to create, maintain, and share research software (Zenodo, GitHub, GitLab). I spoke about the different types of licenses that can be attached to the outputs of the research. This was followed by a summary of the journey of the &lt;a href="https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Research Software Engineering (RSE) Asia Association&lt;/a>, which I co-founded and co-lead since its launch in 2021.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>🔑 &lt;strong>Talk Resources:&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>Slides: Jyoti Bhogal. (2024, August 27). What is Research Software and Why Should we Think About its Sustainability?. Zenodo.&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.13377699" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.13377699&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Recording: &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=giTd8lN88KQ" target="_blank" rel="noopener">APAN58 : Asia Pacific Open and Sharing Data WG, 27th August 2024, Part 1&lt;/a> (Clip from 00:00 to 14:55)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/giTd8lN88KQ?si=7P9Tu7Kj90rscXgm&amp;amp;start=1" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen>&lt;/iframe>
&lt;p>As I spoke about research software, its definition, the tools to write and maintain it, the audience became curious to know more about research software and the community around it. For the OSDWG session, which focused on topics like Open Science and how research software complements it, my presentation actually gave a keynote kind of a head start to the rest of the talks being presented in the session of OSDWG.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="APAN58 Presentation Task" srcset="
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-03-30_apan58_apan59_blog/APAN58_talk_image_2_task_hu11503873997529272157.webp 400w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-03-30_apan58_apan59_blog/APAN58_talk_image_2_task_hu17643718055601053226.webp 760w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-03-30_apan58_apan59_blog/APAN58_talk_image_2_task_hu9113764437418880555.webp 1200w"
src="https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-03-30_apan58_apan59_blog/APAN58_talk_image_2_task_hu11503873997529272157.webp"
width="760"
height="341"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;em>Source&lt;/em>: &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=giTd8lN88KQ" target="_blank" rel="noopener">APAN58 : Asia Pacific Open and Sharing Data WG, 27th August 2024, Part 1&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Towards the end of my talk, I asked the audience to share their feedback to the questions ‘What do you think about research software engineering as a role and as a career path?’ and ‘What are your thoughts on how open science might help the researchers worldwide?’ and received some interesting responses:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>“Looks interesting, since I have heard about it for the very first time in this talk at APAN58 meeting.”&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>“It is necessary for research software engineering management. I’ve heard that the organisations usually do not have enough capacity for managing research software engineers. However, they need software consistently. So, the public sectors help with this.”&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>“It&amp;rsquo;s an innovative way to share research, data and publications, etc.”&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>“So many students in the world have a very different situation in their social and life environment. For them, the internet and open science involving open access, open data, open software, and so on will help provide an education and research environment for equality.”&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>It was nice to see that my talk sparked curiosity in the audience and they promptly provided their feedback of what resonated with them. I also attended sessions on various topics including cybersecurity, high-performance computing &amp;amp; AI, agriculture and rural hybridization, network technologies, telemedicine and research collaborations. These sessions gave me more insights into the latest proceedings in the various fields of research and development in the Asia Pacific region.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In March 2025, I had the opportunity to speak at the &lt;strong>Asia Pacific Advanced Network’s APAN59 meeting&lt;/strong> online remotely. My presentation was on the title &lt;em>&lt;strong>‘Building Bridges: Advancing Research Software Engineering and Open Science in Asia’&lt;/strong>&lt;/em>. I gave my talk as part of the APAN’s Open and Sharing Data Working Group (OSDWG). Software being one of the pillars of Open Science, through this talk, I highlighted how paying attention towards developing and maintaining research software is directly linked to the principles of Open Science.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Later in March 2025, I had the opportunity to present my talk titled &lt;em>&lt;strong>‘Building Bridges: Advancing Research Software Engineering and Open Science in Asia’&lt;/strong>&lt;/em> at &lt;strong>APAN59,&lt;/strong> online remotely again as part of the OSDWG discussion session. Software being one of the pillars of Open Science, through this talk, I highlighted how paying attention towards developing and maintaining research software is directly linked to the principles of Open Science.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>During my talk, I shared about my ongoing &lt;strong>Research Study on the Research Software Engineering (RSEng) Landscape in Asia&lt;/strong>. I discussed the need of this study - due to the &lt;strong>no/low representation of the community of researchers who code in the Asian region&lt;/strong>. This is demonstrated by the outcomes of an existing global survey by the Software Sustainability Institute, which completely lacks representation from Asia.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="SSI Survey Summary Table" srcset="
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-03-30_apan58_apan59_blog/ssi_survey_summary_table_hu14328662006185527097.webp 400w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-03-30_apan58_apan59_blog/ssi_survey_summary_table_hu12058655987869181435.webp 760w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-03-30_apan58_apan59_blog/ssi_survey_summary_table_hu17883893208372967848.webp 1200w"
src="https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-03-30_apan58_apan59_blog/ssi_survey_summary_table_hu14328662006185527097.webp"
width="760"
height="564"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Source: Article by SSI: &lt;a href="https://www.software.ac.uk/blog/what-do-we-know-about-rses-results-our-international-surveys" target="_blank" rel="noopener">What do we know about RSEs? Results from our international surveys&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="SSI Survey Map" srcset="
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-03-30_apan58_apan59_blog/ssi_survey_map_hu15950245902033643575.webp 400w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-03-30_apan58_apan59_blog/ssi_survey_map_hu11096678663734903656.webp 760w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-03-30_apan58_apan59_blog/ssi_survey_map_hu672506643558864757.webp 1200w"
src="https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-03-30_apan58_apan59_blog/ssi_survey_map_hu15950245902033643575.webp"
width="760"
height="375"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Source: Article by SSI: &lt;a href="https://www.software.ac.uk/blog/what-do-we-know-about-rses-results-our-international-surveys" target="_blank" rel="noopener">What do we know about RSEs? Results from our international surveys&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I shared the roadmap of my research study with the audience. At the end of my talk, there were quite a few engaging questions. One of the comments from an active member of the APAN biannual meetings was&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>“The topic of this research study is something that deals with a national-level problem, thus making it much more essential to be studied.”&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>The appreciative feedback encourages me to keep taking my research work further.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>🔑 &lt;strong>Talk Resources:&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>Bhogal, J. (2025, March 3). Building Bridges: Advancing Research Software Engineering and Open Science in Asia. Zenodo. &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.15180196" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.15180196&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h3 id="learn-more-about-us">&lt;strong>Learn More About Us&lt;/strong>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>For more information and to join upcoming events, visit:&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="rse-asia">RSE Asia&lt;/h4>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Website: &lt;a href="https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>For the latest news, events, activities, and opportunities, follow us on our &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/company/rse-asia-association/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">LinkedIn page&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>To join the RSE Asia community, please fill out our short &lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/forms/d/1XSxDaTJzcNyGeDYXyJNVg1TDCo7un18PLFNiK6_jL2g/edit" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Community Membership Form&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul></description></item><item><title>Funding for Research Software</title><link>https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/event/2025-03-20-ep-6-rs-fund/</link><pubDate>Thu, 20 Mar 2025 08:30:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/event/2025-03-20-ep-6-rs-fund/</guid><description>&lt;p>In the last episode of the series on &amp;lsquo;Enabling Open Science through Research Code&amp;rsquo;, we will explore opportunities related to funding for research software-related work.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>20 March 2025 @ 8:30 - 10:00 am UTC &lt;a href="https://www.timeanddate.com/worldclock/fixedtime.html?msg=Research&amp;#43;Software&amp;#43;Funding&amp;amp;iso=20250320T0830&amp;amp;p1=1440&amp;amp;ah=1&amp;amp;am=30" target="_blank" rel="noopener">(see in your local time)&lt;/a>&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>&lt;a href="https://us06web.zoom.us/meeting/register/tZwodO2pqD0rGtUTKdPjxP2j2X1gFioPn2bo#/registration" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Register now&lt;/a>&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="our-speakers">Our Speakers&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>&lt;a href="https://bsky.app/profile/neocarlitos.bsky.social" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Carlos Martinez-Ortiz&lt;/a>&lt;/strong>,
Scientific Community Manager, &lt;em>Netherlands eScience Center&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Carlos is a Community Manager at the &lt;a href="https://www.esciencecenter.nl/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Netherlands eScience Center&lt;/a>. His work focuses on topics related to software sustainability at the eScience Center, advancing its goal to empower researchers by collaboratively designing sustainable software, and building digital skills and expertise.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>&lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/colettebos/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Colette Bos&lt;/a>&lt;/strong>,
Programme Director &lt;em>Netherlands eScience Center&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Colette holds a PhD in research policy/research sociology and has extensive experience in research policy, research funding, impact of science evaluations and open science. She has worked at the &lt;a href="https://www.esciencecenter.nl/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Netherlands eScience Center&lt;/a> for two years as Programme Director where she is responsible for the project portfolio of the center.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>&lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/gemma-turon/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Gemma Turon Rodrigo&lt;/a>&lt;/strong>, Executive Director, &lt;em>Ersilia Open Source Initiative&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Trained as a molecular biologist, Gemma completed a PhD in colorectal cancer and stem cells at IRB Barcelona in 2019, before taking a one-year break to focus on working and volunteering in the third sector. This shifted her scientific interest to global health and neglected diseases, and the existing barriers to tackle some of the most urgent health issues in developing countries. With &lt;a href="https://www.ersilia.io/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Ersilia&lt;/a>, she aims to explore new ways of community building and engagement in the scientific arena, at the intersection between academia, biotech start-ups and NPOs.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>&lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/gemma-turon/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">John Chevers&lt;/a>&lt;/strong>, Technology Lead, &lt;em>Data for Science and Health, Wellcome Trust&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>John Chevers is Technology Lead in the &lt;a href="https://wellcome.org/who-we-are/teams/data-science-and-health-team" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Data for Science and Health Team&lt;/a> at the Wellcome Trust. He has held leadership roles in industry, the NHS and academia, and has a particular interest in the funding and sustainability of software and data resources. Prior to working in the health sector, John led partnerships and commercial strategy for GEANT, the pan-European internet for research and education. He holds a PhD in Physics and an MSc in electrical engineering.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>&lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/joseph-wafula-768a2371/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Joseph Wafula&lt;/a>&lt;/strong>, Professor and Lead, &lt;em>African Open Science Platform East Africa Node&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="stay-connected">Stay Connected&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Follow our &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/company/rse-asia-association/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">LinkedIn page&lt;/a> to get the latest updates about this series.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Enabling Open Science Through Research Code: Insights from Episode 5 - Testing Research Code</title><link>https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-02-20-eostrc_ep_5/</link><pubDate>Thu, 20 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-02-20-eostrc_ep_5/</guid><description>&lt;p>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="Episode 5 banner" srcset="
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-02-20-eostrc_ep_5/banner_episode_5_hu11682435593169111521.webp 400w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-02-20-eostrc_ep_5/banner_episode_5_hu3360883658036713126.webp 760w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-02-20-eostrc_ep_5/banner_episode_5_hu14472087816408923083.webp 1200w"
src="https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-02-20-eostrc_ep_5/banner_episode_5_hu11682435593169111521.webp"
width="760"
height="608"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="introduction">&lt;strong>Introduction&lt;/strong>&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>In the world of research software development, &lt;strong>ensuring that code runs correctly and produces reliable results is crucial&lt;/strong>. However, &lt;strong>software testing is often overlooked,&lt;/strong> particularly in academic settings where researchers may lack formal training in programming best practices. This challenge was a central theme in the recent discussion during episode 5 of our six-part series &lt;em>&amp;ldquo;Enabling Open Science Through Research Code&amp;rdquo;,&lt;/em> where experts from diverse backgrounds shared their experiences and insights on making software testing accessible and effective.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>During the session, panellists emphasised that while research software development is often self-taught, adopting best practices such as software testing can improve both individual efficiency and collaboration. One of the mantras that continuously came up in the different episodes is that&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>We should be our own best collaborators first.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Episode 5 once again showed how &lt;em>good coding practices can benefit the coder as much as other contributors, collaborators, and users&lt;/em>. This post summarises the discussion, highlighting practical tips for beginners and more advanced strategies for experienced developers.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Our wonderful speakers included:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-4420-0656" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Abhishek Dasgupta&lt;/a>, Senior Research Software Engineer at Oxford Research Software Engineering group, University of Oxford, UK&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/saranjeet-k-48ab769b/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Saranjeet Kaur Bhogal&lt;/a>, Research Software Engineer at Imperial College London, UK and co-founder of the RSE Asia Association&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/sheena-o-connell-0bb72527/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Sheena O&amp;rsquo;Connell&lt;/a>, Software developer, founder and trainer at Prelude, South Africa&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="tips-tools-and-practices-for-novices">&lt;strong>Tips, Tools, and Practices for Novices&lt;/strong>&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>If you&amp;rsquo;re new to coding or research software development, software testing may seem like an advanced topic. However, as our panellists suggest, starting with simple practices can make a big difference in the reliability of your code.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="1-start-with-assertions">&lt;strong>1. Start with Assertions&lt;/strong>&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Assertions are a lightweight way to check that your code behaves as expected. Sheena shared an example from her experience, explaining how beginners often overlook errors that could easily be caught by using &lt;code>assert&lt;/code> statements in Python.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Assertions act as built-in sanity checks and can help catch errors early before they lead to misleading research results.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="2-use-smoke-testing">&lt;strong>2. Use Smoke Testing&lt;/strong>&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Simply running your code from start to finish to ensure it doesn’t crash is an easy way to catch obvious issues. Sheena described this as a useful technique for those who may not yet have structured testing frameworks in place.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Automated tools like &lt;code>nbval&lt;/code> can help validate Jupyter Notebooks by checking that expected outputs remain consistent, an approach that Abhishek recommended.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="3-learn-basic-unit-testing">&lt;strong>3. Learn Basic Unit Testing&lt;/strong>&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Unit tests check individual functions or small sections of code. Abhishek stressed that even a simple test like &lt;code>assert 2 + 3 == 5&lt;/code> is a great first step.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>In Python, &lt;code>pytest&lt;/code> is a lightweight and easy-to-use testing framework, whereas in R, &lt;code>testthat&lt;/code> provides a simple way to implement tests within research code.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="4-keep-code-modular">&lt;strong>4. Keep Code Modular&lt;/strong>&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Writing functions instead of long scripts makes it easier to test individual components. As Sheena pointed out, “Untested code is brittle.” Structuring code into reusable functions makes adding tests more straightforward.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="5-automate-where-possible">&lt;strong>5. Automate Where Possible&lt;/strong>&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Using GitHub Actions or other Continuous Integration (CI) tools can automate testing whenever you update your code. Abhishek mentioned that CI is a great way to ensure code works across multiple platforms, which is particularly helpful when collaborating with researchers using different operating systems.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>For R users, the {&lt;code>usethis}&lt;/code> package simplifies the workflow setup, automating repetitive tasks (for both R packages as well as non-package projects), as suggested by Saranjeet. She also recommended using the {&lt;code>fusen}&lt;/code> package for anyone new to R package development (and also for experienced developers while they are prototyping functions) as it involves writing the function as well as its documentation and unit tests in the same file, avoiding the risk of forgetting crucial steps.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="Testing Software, " srcset="
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-02-20-eostrc_ep_5/testing_software_hu1841008672167238983.webp 400w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-02-20-eostrc_ep_5/testing_software_hu7307457166735778221.webp 760w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-02-20-eostrc_ep_5/testing_software_hu5609377495136566095.webp 1200w"
src="https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-02-20-eostrc_ep_5/testing_software_hu1841008672167238983.webp"
width="760"
height="475"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;a href="https://www.softwaretestpro.com/category/cartoon/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Image Credits:Torsten Zelger&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="approaches-to-software-testing-for-experienced-developers">&lt;strong>Approaches to Software Testing for Experienced Developers&lt;/strong>&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>For those already familiar with software development, a more structured approach to testing can improve reproducibility and collaboration. The panellists discussed key strategies for advanced users, including:&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="1-different-types-of-testing">&lt;strong>1. Different Types of Testing&lt;/strong>&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Unit Testing&lt;/strong>: Ensures small, isolated parts of the code work as expected.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Integration Testing&lt;/strong>: Checks if different parts of the system function correctly together. Abhishek highlighted the importance of this, noting that end-to-end validation is often overlooked in research projects.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Regression Testing&lt;/strong>: Ensures new changes don’t break existing functionality, an approach Sheena described as essential for long-term code maintenance.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Property-Based Testing&lt;/strong>: Uses tools like &lt;code>hypothesis&lt;/code> in Python to test code with a range of inputs, uncovering unexpected behaviours. Abhishek noted this as particularly useful for numerical research software.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="2-version-control-and-cicd">&lt;strong>2. Version Control and CI/CD&lt;/strong>&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Git and GitHub/GitLab&lt;/strong>: Version control helps track changes, making it easier to debug issues. Sheena emphasised that &amp;ldquo;researchers who don&amp;rsquo;t use version control end up with folders full of files like &lt;code>final_version_revised_final_final.py&lt;/code>, which is a nightmare to maintain.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Continuous Integration (CI)&lt;/strong>: Running tests automatically on GitHub ensures all code changes are validated before being merged. Abhishek explained that setting up CI allows researchers to avoid relying on manual testing across different machines.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="3-cross-platform-testing">&lt;strong>3. Cross-Platform Testing&lt;/strong>&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Researchers often work across different operating systems. Automating tests in cloud environments ensures compatibility with Windows, macOS, and Linux.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Tools like &lt;code>tox&lt;/code> or &lt;code>nox&lt;/code> (Python) allow testing across multiple versions of a language. Abhishek highlighted that CI workflows, once set up, eliminate the need to manually ask colleagues to test code on different platforms.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="4-automating-data-validations">&lt;strong>4. Automating Data Validations&lt;/strong>&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Data quality is critical in research. Sheena introduced &lt;code>pandera&lt;/code> in Python, a tool that helps verify data integrity and data schemas before analysis.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Statistical validation using libraries like &lt;code>scipy.stats&lt;/code> can confirm that distributions match expected properties, an approach recommended for data-intensive projects.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="5-balancing-testing-with-research-deadlines">&lt;strong>5. Balancing Testing with Research Deadlines&lt;/strong>&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Writing tests may seem like extra work, but it prevents time-consuming debugging later. Abhishek acknowledged that &amp;ldquo;getting 100% test coverage is impractical for most research projects, but basic integration tests should be a minimum.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Using automated tools like R’s &lt;code>targets&lt;/code> package helps manage computational workflows efficiently, only re-running necessary parts of the code. Saranjeet recommended this as a time-saving approach for researchers handling large datasets.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="conclusion">&lt;strong>Conclusion&lt;/strong>&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Software testing is not just for professional developers—it is an essential practice for research reproducibility and collaboration. While beginners can start with simple assertions and unit tests, advanced users can implement continuous integration, property-based testing, and automated data validation to ensure code reliability.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As Anelda concluded,&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Testing is not just about making research more open; it’s about being your own best &amp;gt; collaborator.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>By integrating these testing strategies into research software development, we can move toward a more open, transparent, and reliable scientific ecosystem.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>📢 &lt;strong>Explore More:&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Access our &lt;a href="https://zenodo.org/records/14961866" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Resource Sheet&lt;/a>, which contains numerous valuable resources shared by the panellists, facilitators, and participants.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>View the &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Q_x5SFrkol4&amp;amp;t=9s" target="_blank" rel="noopener">session recording&lt;/a> on YouTube.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>The first draft of this blog post was created with ChatGPT from the edited video transcript.&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="looking-ahead">&lt;strong>Looking Ahead&lt;/strong>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The next episode in the series, &lt;strong>&amp;ldquo;Research Software Funding&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong> will take place on &lt;strong>March 20, 2025, at 08:30 UTC.&lt;/strong> Be sure to register &lt;a href="https://us06web.zoom.us/meeting/register/tZwodO2pqD0rGtUTKdPjxP2j2X1gFioPn2bo#/registration" target="_blank" rel="noopener">here&lt;/a> and join the conversation!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This series is an excellent opportunity to learn, connect, and grow as we work together to enable open science - one line of code at a time.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>This meetup series is a collaboration between Talarify, RSSE Africa, RSE Asia, AREN, and ReSA.&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h3 id="learn-more-about-us">&lt;strong>Learn More About Us&lt;/strong>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>For more information and to join upcoming events, visit:&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="rsse-africa">RSSE Africa&lt;/h4>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Website: &lt;a href="https://rsse.africa" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://rsse.africa&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Sign up for our newsletter: &lt;a href="https://talarify.us14.list-manage.com/subscribe?u=35d5db26d3b108b9ef9b9ac43&amp;amp;id=55e9f5a692" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://talarify.us14.list-manage.com/subscribe?u=35d5db26d3b108b9ef9b9ac43&amp;id=55e9f5a692&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Join our LinkedIn group, where you can also share information with the broader community: &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/groups/12903402/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://www.linkedin.com/groups/12903402/&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h4 id="rse-asia">RSE Asia&lt;/h4>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Website: &lt;a href="https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>For the latest news, events, activities, and opportunities, follow us on our &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/company/rse-asia-association/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">LinkedIn page&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>To join the RSE Asia community, please fill out our short &lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/forms/d/1XSxDaTJzcNyGeDYXyJNVg1TDCo7un18PLFNiK6_jL2g/edit" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Community Membership Form&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h4 id="aren">AREN&lt;/h4>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Website: &lt;a href="https://africanrn.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://africanrn.org/&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Sign up: &lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLSeeFkD5A4D9l6ncQWjKBiI-GqBOzL-JMe7Fx3ijUYEjHjDUoQ/viewform" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLSeeFkD5A4D9l6ncQWjKBiI-GqBOzL-JMe7Fx3ijUYEjHjDUoQ/viewform&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h4 id="resa">ReSA&lt;/h4>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Website: &lt;a href="https://www.researchsoft.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://www.researchsoft.org/&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Sign up for the newsletter: &lt;a href="https://www.researchsoft.org/news/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://www.researchsoft.org/news/&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The &lt;a href="https://ogyaqy.clicks.mlsend.com/ty/c/eyJ2Ijoie1wiYVwiOjc3ODEyOSxcImxcIjoxMzM1MDk5NDcxNDA4Njc3OTMsXCJyXCI6MTMzNTA5OTQ4NTg4OTUwNzkzfSIsInMiOiJiMTU2Y2FhYzI3YjQyZjI1In0" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Amsterdam Declaration on Funding Research Software Sustainability&lt;/a>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Become a signatory: &lt;a href="https://adore.software/sign/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://adore.software/sign/&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul></description></item><item><title>Enabling Open Science through Research Code: Insights from Episode 4 - Documentation for Research Code</title><link>https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-02-20-eosrtc_ep_4/</link><pubDate>Thu, 20 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-02-20-eosrtc_ep_4/</guid><description>&lt;p>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="Episode 4 banner" srcset="
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-02-20-eosrtc_ep_4/banner_episode_4_hu10657716727155207352.webp 400w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-02-20-eosrtc_ep_4/banner_episode_4_hu15894016203414037924.webp 760w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-02-20-eosrtc_ep_4/banner_episode_4_hu18437337149325435449.webp 1200w"
src="https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-02-20-eosrtc_ep_4/banner_episode_4_hu10657716727155207352.webp"
width="760"
height="608"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Imagine you’ve spent months crafting a complex research software tool, refining algorithms, and running countless simulations. It works brilliantly—but then, six months later, you revisit the code and… you’re lost. Sounds familiar? You’re not alone. Experts shared their experiences and strategies for writing good documentation in the fourth episode of the Research Software Community Conversations Series titled &lt;a href="https://rsse.africa/community_meetups" target="_blank" rel="noopener">&lt;strong>Enabling Open Science through Research Code&lt;/strong>&lt;/a>. Here’s what we learned from our participants and insightful panellists:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/thisisjennywong/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">&lt;strong>Jenny Wong&lt;/strong>&lt;/a> - Product Manager @ 2i2c (UK/US)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.joelnitta.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">&lt;strong>Joel Nitta&lt;/strong>&lt;/a> - Associate Professor @ Chiba University (Japan)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/mthetho-sovara-3a939272/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">&lt;strong>Mthetho Sovara&lt;/strong>&lt;/a> - Centre for High-Performance Computing (CHPC), National Integrated Cyberinfrastructure System (NICIS) CSIR (South Africa)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="-why-documentation-is-essential">&lt;strong>📌 Why Documentation is Essential&lt;/strong>&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>🚀 &lt;strong>Boosts Reproducibility:&lt;/strong> Research software often accompanies papers, but results can be difficult to replicate without documentation. As &lt;strong>Jenny&lt;/strong> pointed out, in fluid dynamics research, well-documented simulation codes gained more adoption than poorly documented alternatives.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>🤝 &lt;strong>Facilitates Collaboration:&lt;/strong> Well-documented projects attract more contributors and streamline knowledge transfer. &lt;strong>Joel&lt;/strong> shared his experience in the rOpenSci community, where clear documentation allowed him to take over and improve an existing R package without needing direct input from the original creator.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>⏳ &lt;strong>Enhances Longevity:&lt;/strong> Code without documentation quickly becomes unusable—even by its original authors! &lt;strong>Mthetho&lt;/strong> described how well-documented software in weather forecasting led to unexpected collaborations with the South African Weather Service and Ethiopian researchers.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>🔓 &lt;strong>Promotes Open Science:&lt;/strong> Accessible research software fosters innovation and inclusion worldwide. &lt;strong>Jenny&lt;/strong> emphasised that accessible documentation enables wider adoption of tools, making scientific computing more democratic.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="-common-challenges--solutions">&lt;strong>🔥 Common Challenges &amp;amp; Solutions&lt;/strong>&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>⏰ &lt;strong>Time Constraints&lt;/strong> → Write minimal but clear documentation as you code. &lt;strong>Joel&lt;/strong> suggested that legible code, such as meaningful variable names instead of “x” or “dat”, is itself a form of documentation that is even better than comments.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>🧩 &lt;strong>Lack of Standardisation&lt;/strong> → Use templates and structured frameworks. &lt;strong>Mthetho&lt;/strong> mentioned that clear, structured guides helped non-computational scientists successfully use OpenFOAM in unexpected fields like environmental science.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>🎯 &lt;strong>Technical vs. User Documentation&lt;/strong> → Engage users in documentation efforts for clarity. &lt;strong>Jenny&lt;/strong> highlighted the role of community-driven documentation efforts, such as hackathons, to improve usability.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="-best-practices-for-better-documentation">&lt;strong>🛠 Best Practices for Better Documentation&lt;/strong>&lt;/h2>
&lt;h3 id="-1-write-as-you-code">&lt;strong>✍️ 1. Write as You Code&lt;/strong>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Waiting until the end leads to missing details. Add inline comments and README files &lt;strong>while developing&lt;/strong>. &lt;strong>Joel&lt;/strong> emphasised that tools like RMarkdown (and its successor, Quarto) can be used for &lt;strong>literate programming&lt;/strong>—thereby ensuring that the results of code are automatically generated alongside their description.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="-2-differentiate-documentation-types">&lt;strong>🔄 2. Differentiate Documentation Types&lt;/strong>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>✔ &lt;strong>User-facing documentation:&lt;/strong> How to install, use, and troubleshoot.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>✔ &lt;strong>Developer-facing documentation:&lt;/strong> Comments, API references, contribution guides.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="-3-use-the-right-tools">&lt;strong>📚 3. Use the Right Tools&lt;/strong>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>📄 &lt;strong>Markdown &amp;amp; Jupyter Notebooks&lt;/strong> – Combine narrative and code.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>📝 &lt;strong>Quarto &amp;amp; R Markdown&lt;/strong> – For structured research outputs.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>📘 &lt;strong>Sphinx &amp;amp; MIST&lt;/strong> – Python-based documentation frameworks.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>🌐 &lt;strong>GitHub Wikis &amp;amp; Pages&lt;/strong> – Host documentation openly.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>🤖 &lt;strong>AI-based tools (e.g., Cursor, Copilot)&lt;/strong> – Assist with documentation (but always review!).&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="-4-community--collaboration-matter">&lt;strong>🤝 4. Community &amp;amp; Collaboration Matter&lt;/strong>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>💡 Participate in documentation hackathons. &lt;strong>Jenny&lt;/strong> shared how Project Pythia’s hackathons provided a structured way to improve documentation in geospatial science. 🌍 Join communities like &lt;strong>Project Pythia&lt;/strong>, &lt;strong>The Carpentries&lt;/strong>, and &lt;strong>Write the Docs&lt;/strong>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="-5-advocate-for-funding--policy-support">&lt;strong>💰 5. Advocate for Funding &amp;amp; Policy Support&lt;/strong>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>📢 Push for documentation funding in grant proposals.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>🏛 Engage with funders to integrate documentation into open science policies.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="-future-of-documentation-ai--automation">&lt;strong>🚀 Future of Documentation: AI &amp;amp; Automation&lt;/strong>&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>🤖 &lt;strong>Automated Documentation:&lt;/strong> AI tools generate initial drafts, saving researchers time. However, while helpful, AI-assisted documentation should always be reviewed for accuracy.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>🌍 &lt;strong>AI for Translation:&lt;/strong> Helps make documentation accessible in multiple languages, fostering global inclusivity. &lt;strong>Anelda&lt;/strong> highlighted how AI tools might support research documentation in multilingual communities in the future. For now, we still need a human-in-the-loop translator for translation efforts. Especially for low-resourced languages.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>⚠️ &lt;strong>Caution Needed:&lt;/strong> AI-generated content must be reviewed for accuracy and ethical considerations. &lt;strong>Jenny&lt;/strong> raised concerns about biases in AI and the environmental impact of large-scale machine learning models.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="-final-thoughts-make-documentation-a-priority">&lt;strong>🎯 Final Thoughts: Make Documentation a Priority&lt;/strong>&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Great research code deserves great documentation. It makes work reproducible, fosters collaboration, and ensures that software remains usable long after its creator has moved on. By embracing best practices and community support, we can all contribute to a culture where documentation is seen not as a burden—but as a fundamental part of open science.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>📢 &lt;strong>Explore More:&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Access our &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.14833913" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Resource Sheet&lt;/a>, which contains numerous valuable resources shared by the panellists, facilitators, and participants.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>View the &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/6GJZ8mO4t9Q" target="_blank" rel="noopener">session recording&lt;/a> on YouTube.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>The first draft of this blog post was created with ChatGPT from the edited video transcript.&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="looking-ahead">&lt;strong>Looking Ahead&lt;/strong>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The next episode in the series, &lt;strong>&amp;ldquo;Testing Research Code&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong> will take place on &lt;strong>February 20, 2025, at 08:30 UTC.&lt;/strong> Be sure to register &lt;a href="https://us06web.zoom.us/meeting/register/tZArd-GvqzkiGt13BRkCV_4mAIa0uRWeGgeE#/registration" target="_blank" rel="noopener">here&lt;/a> and join the conversation!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For those who missed Episode 4, a &lt;a href="%20https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.14833913">resources sheet&lt;/a> with tips and the &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/6GJZ8mO4t9Q" target="_blank" rel="noopener">session recording&lt;/a> on YouTube is available. This series is an excellent opportunity to learn, connect, and grow as we work together to enable open science - one line of code at a time.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>This meetup series is a collaboration between Talarify, RSSE Africa, RSE Asia, AREN, and ReSA.&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h3 id="learn-more-about-us">&lt;strong>Learn More About Us&lt;/strong>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>For more information and to join upcoming events, visit:&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="rsse-africa">RSSE Africa&lt;/h4>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Website: &lt;a href="https://rsse.africa" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://rsse.africa&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Sign up for our newsletter: &lt;a href="https://talarify.us14.list-manage.com/subscribe?u=35d5db26d3b108b9ef9b9ac43&amp;amp;id=55e9f5a692" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://talarify.us14.list-manage.com/subscribe?u=35d5db26d3b108b9ef9b9ac43&amp;id=55e9f5a692&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Join our LinkedIn group, where you can also share information with the broader community: &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/groups/12903402/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://www.linkedin.com/groups/12903402/&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h4 id="rse-asia">RSE Asia&lt;/h4>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Website: &lt;a href="https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>For the latest news, events, activities, and opportunities, follow us on our &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/company/rse-asia-association/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">LinkedIn page&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>To join the RSE Asia community, please fill out our short &lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/forms/d/1XSxDaTJzcNyGeDYXyJNVg1TDCo7un18PLFNiK6_jL2g/edit" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Community Membership Form&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h4 id="aren">AREN&lt;/h4>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Website: &lt;a href="https://africanrn.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://africanrn.org/&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Sign up: &lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLSeeFkD5A4D9l6ncQWjKBiI-GqBOzL-JMe7Fx3ijUYEjHjDUoQ/viewform" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLSeeFkD5A4D9l6ncQWjKBiI-GqBOzL-JMe7Fx3ijUYEjHjDUoQ/viewform&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h4 id="resa">ReSA&lt;/h4>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Website: &lt;a href="https://www.researchsoft.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://www.researchsoft.org/&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Sign up for the newsletter: &lt;a href="https://www.researchsoft.org/news/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://www.researchsoft.org/news/&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The &lt;a href="https://ogyaqy.clicks.mlsend.com/ty/c/eyJ2Ijoie1wiYVwiOjc3ODEyOSxcImxcIjoxMzM1MDk5NDcxNDA4Njc3OTMsXCJyXCI6MTMzNTA5OTQ4NTg4OTUwNzkzfSIsInMiOiJiMTU2Y2FhYzI3YjQyZjI1In0" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Amsterdam Declaration on Funding Research Software Sustainability&lt;/a>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Become a signatory: &lt;a href="https://adore.software/sign/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://adore.software/sign/&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul></description></item><item><title>Enabling Open Science through Research Code: Insights from Episode 3 - Opening up Research Code</title><link>https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-02-18-eostrc_ep_3/</link><pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-02-18-eostrc_ep_3/</guid><description>&lt;p>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="Episode 3 banner" srcset="
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-02-18-eostrc_ep_3/banner_episode_3_hu16823332255986876825.webp 400w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-02-18-eostrc_ep_3/banner_episode_3_hu13943160536365637616.webp 760w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-02-18-eostrc_ep_3/banner_episode_3_hu715965164664889172.webp 1200w"
src="https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-02-18-eostrc_ep_3/banner_episode_3_hu16823332255986876825.webp"
width="760"
height="608"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In December 2024, we hosted episode four of our six-part series on Enabling Opening Science through Research Code. This time, we focused on openly sharing research code. The conversation provided invaluable insights into best practices, challenges, and the impact of open source in research. Whether you are a researcher, software developer, or just getting started, here are the key takeaways from this inspiring discussion.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="why-open-research-code-matters">&lt;strong>Why Open Research Code Matters&lt;/strong>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Research software plays a crucial role in scientific discovery. Making it openly accessible enhances transparency, reproducibility, and collaboration. The discussion highlighted several reasons why open code can be beneficial to those who develop it as well as the broader research community:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Reproducibility &amp;amp; Credibility&lt;/strong>: When researchers share their code, others can validate and build upon it, ensuring scientific integrity.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Collaboration &amp;amp; Community Growth&lt;/strong>: Open software enables researchers and developers worldwide to work together, improving tools and methodologies.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Increased Citations &amp;amp; Impact&lt;/strong>: Studies with accessible code tend to receive more citations, increasing the visibility and influence of the research.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Funding &amp;amp; Institutional Support&lt;/strong>: Many funding agencies now require researchers to share code and data as part of open science initiatives.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="challenges-and-how-to-overcome-them">&lt;strong>Challenges and How to Overcome Them&lt;/strong>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>While making code open has clear benefits, it comes with its own set of challenges. Speakers shared personal experiences and solutions to common obstacles:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Fear of Criticism&lt;/strong>: Many researchers worry that sharing their code may invite scrutiny. However, constructive feedback leads to improved code quality.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Maintaining Code Over Time&lt;/strong>: Researchers often move on to new projects and cannot maintain old code. One solution is to create a community around a project, inviting contributors to help maintain and improve it.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Data Privacy &amp;amp; Intellectual Property&lt;/strong>: Researchers must anonymise datasets or create synthetic versions that simulate actual data while maintaining confidentiality when dealing with sensitive data.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Documentation &amp;amp; Reusability&lt;/strong>: A well-documented project is far more valuable to others. Providing README files, usage instructions, and licensing information makes it easier for others to use and contribute.
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>We talk more about documentation in &lt;a href="https://zenodo.org/records/14833914" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Episode 4&lt;/a>!&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="best-practices-for-sharing-research-code">&lt;strong>Best Practices for Sharing Research Code&lt;/strong>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>To make code truly open and useful, researchers can consider the following best practices:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Use Version Control Platforms&lt;/strong>: Platforms like GitHub, GitLab, and Bitbucket facilitate collaboration, version tracking, and code sharing.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Choose an Appropriate License&lt;/strong>: Open source licenses like MIT, Apache 2.0, and GPL define how others can use and modify the code.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Provide Clear Documentation&lt;/strong>: A README file explaining installation, usage, dependencies, and citation details makes the code accessible to others.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Include Citation Information&lt;/strong>: Using a &lt;code>CITATION.cff&lt;/code> file ensures that researchers get credit for their work when their code is used in publications.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Use Containerisation for Reproducibility&lt;/strong>: Tools like Docker and GitHub Code Spaces help ensure that code runs the same way on different machines.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Leverage Community Support&lt;/strong>: Engaging with communities like Research Software Engineering (RSE) groups, The Carpentries, and others provides learning opportunities and networking.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;h3 id="diverse-perspectives-on-open-science">&lt;strong>Diverse Perspectives on Open Science&lt;/strong>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The discussion brought together speakers from various backgrounds, including bioinformatics, linguistics, software engineering, and illustration. Their stories emphasised that open science is not just for software developers but also for researchers and creatives working in different fields.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://linkedin.com/in/adeyinkaoresanya" target="_blank" rel="noopener">&lt;strong>Adeyinka Oresanya&lt;/strong>&lt;/a>&lt;strong>,&lt;/strong> a &lt;strong>software developer&lt;/strong> &lt;strong>at CHAOSS&lt;/strong> in Nigeria&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/chioma-onyido/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">&lt;strong>Chioma Onyido&lt;/strong>&lt;/a>, a &lt;strong>bioinformatician&lt;/strong> from Nigeria, shared how &lt;strong>Bioconductor&lt;/strong>, an open-source project for bioinformatics, has been instrumental in her work.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/mars-lee/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">&lt;strong>Mars Lee&lt;/strong>&lt;/a>, a &lt;strong>technical illustrator&lt;/strong>, highlighted the importance of visual documentation to make open source more accessible.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Kate-Huddlestone" target="_blank" rel="noopener">&lt;strong>Kate Huddlestone&lt;/strong>&lt;/a>&lt;strong>, a linguist&lt;/strong> at Stellenbosch University in South Africa, shared how open-source tools enabled her to work with sign language data, significantly advancing her research.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://orcid.org/0009-0003-0208-8480" target="_blank" rel="noopener">&lt;strong>Juan Pablo&lt;/strong>&lt;/a>&lt;strong>, a senior program manager at GitHub&lt;/strong>, discussed how GitHub provides tools like citation files and ORCID integration to make research software more discoverable and citable.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="final-advice-for-researchers-interested-in-open-code">&lt;strong>Final Advice for Researchers Interested in Open Code&lt;/strong>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Each speaker shared a key piece of advice for those looking to engage in open research software:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Join a Community&lt;/strong>: Engaging with open-source and research communities provides learning and collaboration opportunities.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Take Small Steps&lt;/strong>: Even minimal documentation, a simple README, or choosing a license makes a big difference.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Leverage Available Resources&lt;/strong>: Many educational institutions provide free access to GitHub tools and training programs.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Don’t Fear Making Mistakes&lt;/strong>: Sharing imperfect code is better than keeping it inaccessible. The community will help improve it.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="conclusion">&lt;strong>Conclusion&lt;/strong>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Opening research code benefits both individual researchers and the broader scientific community. By embracing best practices and leveraging community support, researchers can enhance collaboration, improve research reproducibility, and increase the impact of their work. Whether you are just starting or looking to improve your open science practices, remember that engagement, documentation, and a willingness to share and learn are the keys to success.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>The first draft of this blog post was created with ChatGPT from the edited video transcript.&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="looking-ahead">&lt;strong>Looking Ahead&lt;/strong>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The next episode in the series, &lt;strong>&amp;ldquo;Documentation for Research Code&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong> will take place on &lt;strong>January 23, 2025, at 08:30 UTC.&lt;/strong> Be sure to register &lt;a href="https://us06web.zoom.us/meeting/register/tZ0scOmspz0iH9IMt4yxc0O37uEUUiPxYDxa#/registration" target="_blank" rel="noopener">here&lt;/a> and join the conversation!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For those who missed Episode 3, a &lt;a href="https://zenodo.org/records/14833789" target="_blank" rel="noopener">resources sheet&lt;/a> with tips and the &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=cDq9UMSOkhs" target="_blank" rel="noopener">session recording&lt;/a> is available. This series is an excellent opportunity to learn, connect, and grow as we work together to enable open science - one line of code at a time.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>This meetup series is a collaboration between Talarify, RSSE Africa, RSE Asia, AREN, and ReSA.&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h3 id="learn-more-about-us">&lt;strong>Learn More About Us&lt;/strong>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>For more information and to join upcoming events, visit:&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="rsse-africa">RSSE Africa&lt;/h4>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Website: &lt;a href="https://rsse.africa" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://rsse.africa&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Sign up for our newsletter: &lt;a href="https://talarify.us14.list-manage.com/subscribe?u=35d5db26d3b108b9ef9b9ac43&amp;amp;id=55e9f5a692" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://talarify.us14.list-manage.com/subscribe?u=35d5db26d3b108b9ef9b9ac43&amp;id=55e9f5a692&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Join our LinkedIn group, where you can also share information with the broader community: &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/groups/12903402/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://www.linkedin.com/groups/12903402/&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h4 id="rse-asia">RSE Asia&lt;/h4>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Website: &lt;a href="https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>For the latest news, events, activities, and opportunities, follow us on our &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/company/rse-asia-association/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">LinkedIn page&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>To join the RSE Asia community, please fill out our short &lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/forms/d/1XSxDaTJzcNyGeDYXyJNVg1TDCo7un18PLFNiK6_jL2g/edit" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Community Membership Form&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h4 id="aren">AREN&lt;/h4>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Website: &lt;a href="https://africanrn.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://africanrn.org/&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Sign up: &lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLSeeFkD5A4D9l6ncQWjKBiI-GqBOzL-JMe7Fx3ijUYEjHjDUoQ/viewform" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLSeeFkD5A4D9l6ncQWjKBiI-GqBOzL-JMe7Fx3ijUYEjHjDUoQ/viewform&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h4 id="resa">ReSA&lt;/h4>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Website: &lt;a href="https://www.researchsoft.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://www.researchsoft.org/&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Sign up for the newsletter: &lt;a href="https://www.researchsoft.org/news/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://www.researchsoft.org/news/&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The &lt;a href="https://ogyaqy.clicks.mlsend.com/ty/c/eyJ2Ijoie1wiYVwiOjc3ODEyOSxcImxcIjoxMzM1MDk5NDcxNDA4Njc3OTMsXCJyXCI6MTMzNTA5OTQ4NTg4OTUwNzkzfSIsInMiOiJiMTU2Y2FhYzI3YjQyZjI1In0" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Amsterdam Declaration on Funding Research Software Sustainability&lt;/a>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Become a signatory: &lt;a href="https://adore.software/sign/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://adore.software/sign/&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul></description></item><item><title>Enabling Open Science Through Research Code: Insights from Episode 2 - Enabling Reproducibility through Research Code</title><link>https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/blog/2024-11-30-eostrc_ep_2/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/blog/2024-11-30-eostrc_ep_2/</guid><description>&lt;p>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="Episode 2 banner" srcset="
/RSE_Asia/blog/2024-11-30-eostrc_ep_2/banner_episode_2_hu2512634401373151681.webp 400w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2024-11-30-eostrc_ep_2/banner_episode_2_hu18001178582922849733.webp 760w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2024-11-30-eostrc_ep_2/banner_episode_2_hu16985270468714770919.webp 1200w"
src="https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/RSE_Asia/blog/2024-11-30-eostrc_ep_2/banner_episode_2_hu2512634401373151681.webp"
width="760"
height="608"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This blog was originally hosted on the &lt;a href="https://rsse.africa/post/2024/12/open-science-episode2/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">RSSE Africa webpage&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The &lt;strong>‘Enabling Open Science Through Research Code’&lt;/strong> meet-up series, co-hosted by &lt;strong>RSSE Africa&lt;/strong> and &lt;strong>RSE Asia&lt;/strong>, continues to build momentum. Episode 2, titled &lt;strong>&amp;ldquo;Enabling Reproducibility Through Research Code,&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong> took place on November 14, 2024, bringing together a diverse group of participants and experts to discuss a cornerstone of open science—reproducibility. A valuable open educational resource related to this topic, which the meetup was based on, is available from &lt;a href="https://coderefinery.github.io/reproducible-research/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">CodeRefinery&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="Reproduciblility through research code" srcset="
/RSE_Asia/blog/2024-11-30-eostrc_ep_2/reproducible_research_code_hu10242678790698111219.webp 400w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2024-11-30-eostrc_ep_2/reproducible_research_code_hu122554981269164661.webp 760w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2024-11-30-eostrc_ep_2/reproducible_research_code_hu15244291253848302224.webp 1200w"
src="https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/RSE_Asia/blog/2024-11-30-eostrc_ep_2/reproducible_research_code_hu10242678790698111219.webp"
width="512"
height="362"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>The Turing Way Community. This illustration is created by Scriberia with The Turing Way community, used under a CC-BY 4.0 licence. DOI: &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.3332807" target="_blank" rel="noopener">10.5281/zenodo.3332807&lt;/a>&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="connecting-researchers-who-code">&lt;strong>Connecting Researchers Who Code&lt;/strong>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>A key goal of this series is to connect researchers who code, especially those in Asia and Africa, with peers worldwide to foster collaboration and support. As **Anelda van der Walt (**RSSE Africa) explained:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>“There are so many researchers who code, but they’re often isolated and don’t have communities to share tools, best practices, or even just to vent about the challenges. We hope this series can be the starting point for those conversations.”&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We welcomed participants from various disciplines, including health-related fields, law, linguistics, and bioinformatics. The audience represented a mix of coding-heavy researchers (spending over 50% of their day coding), less frequent coders, and those just beginning their coding journey.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="meet-the-panel">&lt;strong>Meet the Panel&lt;/strong>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Episode 2 featured a diverse panel of experts who brought their unique perspectives on enabling reproducibility:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Kozo Nishida&lt;/strong>: Project Researcher, Tokyo University of Agriculture and Technology, Japan&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Peter van Heusden&lt;/strong>: Bioinformatician, South African National Bioinformatics Institute/University of the Western Cape, South Africa&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Radovan Bast&lt;/strong>: Research Software Engineer, UiT The Arctic University of Norway, and managing the CodeRefinery project.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="panel-discussion-tips-for-enabling-reproducibility">&lt;strong>Panel Discussion: Tips for Enabling Reproducibility&lt;/strong>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Reproducibility, in its simplest terms, is about ensuring that research findings can be replicated and validated. Without reproducibility, there’s no way to confirm the reliability of scientific results.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Saranjeet Kaur Bhogal&lt;/strong>, one of the session facilitators from RSE Asia, captured this sentiment perfectly when she said:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;Be your own best collaborator.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This idea resonated with all the panellists, who emphasised the importance of documenting workflows and code in a way that’s accessible and understandable—not just for others, but for your future self.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Radovan Bast&lt;/strong> added to this perspective, explaining:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;The person you will collaborate with most within your academic career is your past and future self. We should be kind to our future selves!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Whether six months or years down the line, thorough documentation and explanation of your work ensures you—or anyone else—can reproduce the results.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Kozo Nishida&lt;/strong> shared a practical example from metabolomics research, underlining the challenges of reproducibility in quantifying mass spectrometry data. He explained that creating annotations for mass spec peaks often requires manual tweaks and detailed adjustments. Without thorough documentation and clear steps, reproducing metabolomics quantifications becomes nearly impossible.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Peter van Heusden&lt;/strong> reflected on his experiences entering the field of pathogen bioinformatics. He noted that many research papers described methodologies but often omitted critical details, highlighting the importance of reproducibility. He emphasised:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>“If it’s not in code, it’s not really reproducible.”&lt;br>
For Peter, reproducibility means translating what has been done manually into code, ensuring that workflows are transparent and repeatable.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Radovan Bast&lt;/strong> pointed out that reproducibility encompasses many elements—data, scripts, dependencies, environments, workflows, and more. He acknowledged that achieving perfect reproducibility can be daunting and advised:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>“Don’t let perfect be the enemy of good enough.”&lt;br>
Radovan reminded the audience that reproducibility doesn’t need to be flawless to be valuable. He emphasised the importance of sharing work in a reusable way to avoid reinventing the wheel or wasting time.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="practical-tips-for-ensuring-reproducibility">&lt;strong>Practical Tips for Ensuring Reproducibility&lt;/strong>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The session provided many actionable tips to help researchers make their work more reproducible. These included advice on file types, documentation tools, and simple practices like running code on a different computer to ensure it works across environments.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As with all sessions in the series, a comprehensive resource sheet summarising these tips is available &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.14195613" target="_blank" rel="noopener">here&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="the-importance-of-community-in-reproducibility">&lt;strong>The Importance of Community in Reproducibility&lt;/strong>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The panel stressed how reproducibility benefits not just individual researchers but entire research communities:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Radovan Bast&lt;/strong> stressed that limited time and resources make it essential to &amp;ldquo;stand on the shoulders of others&amp;rdquo; by building on existing tools and workflows rather than starting from scratch every time. However, he cautioned that when using others’ code, researchers should always check the license to ensure they have permission to use it and later share their changes.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Peter van Heusden&lt;/strong> highlighted the importance of structured approaches. Starting projects with standardised templates not only ensures consistency but also makes it easier to reproduce and reuse workflows.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Kozo Nishida&lt;/strong> added that reproducible code enables others to build upon your work, improving entire fields of research. He emphasised the importance of joining communities to share tools, collaborate, and foster reproducibility collectively.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="licensing-and-assisted-coding">&lt;strong>Licensing and Assisted Coding&lt;/strong>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>When using code found online, it’s crucial to respect the provided license and credit the author.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Assisted coding with AI, however, raises unresolved questions about licensing and authorship. The panel noted that clearer guidelines from legal experts are needed as this area continues to evolve. It will be interesting to see how these tools and spaces adapt to address these challenges.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="looking-ahead">&lt;strong>Looking Ahead&lt;/strong>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The next episode in the series, &lt;strong>&amp;ldquo;Opening Up Your Code,&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong> will take place on &lt;strong>December 12, 2024, at 08:30 UTC.&lt;/strong> Be sure to register &lt;a href="https://rsse.africa/events-rsse-africa/2024-12-12/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">here&lt;/a> and join the conversation!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For those who missed Episode 2, a &lt;a href="https://zenodo.org/records/14195614" target="_blank" rel="noopener">resources sheet&lt;/a> with tips and the &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/y0z324Jwn4Y" target="_blank" rel="noopener">session recording&lt;/a> is available. This series is an excellent opportunity to learn, connect, and grow as we work together to enable open science - one line of code at a time.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>This meetup series is a collaboration between Talarify, RSSE Africa, RSE Asia, AREN, and ReSA.&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h3 id="learn-more-about-us">&lt;strong>Learn More About Us&lt;/strong>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>For more information and to join upcoming events, visit:&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="rsse-africa">RSSE Africa&lt;/h4>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Website: &lt;a href="https://rsse.africa" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://rsse.africa&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Sign up for our newsletter: &lt;a href="https://talarify.us14.list-manage.com/subscribe?u=35d5db26d3b108b9ef9b9ac43&amp;amp;id=55e9f5a692" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://talarify.us14.list-manage.com/subscribe?u=35d5db26d3b108b9ef9b9ac43&amp;id=55e9f5a692&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Join our LinkedIn group, where you can also share information with the broader community: &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/groups/12903402/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://www.linkedin.com/groups/12903402/&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h4 id="rse-asia">RSE Asia&lt;/h4>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Website: &lt;a href="https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>For the latest news, events, activities, and opportunities, follow us on our &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/company/rse-asia-association/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">LinkedIn page&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>To join the RSE Asia community, please fill out our short &lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/forms/d/1XSxDaTJzcNyGeDYXyJNVg1TDCo7un18PLFNiK6_jL2g/edit" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Community Membership Form&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h4 id="aren">AREN&lt;/h4>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Website: &lt;a href="https://africanrn.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://africanrn.org/&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Sign up: &lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLSeeFkD5A4D9l6ncQWjKBiI-GqBOzL-JMe7Fx3ijUYEjHjDUoQ/viewform" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLSeeFkD5A4D9l6ncQWjKBiI-GqBOzL-JMe7Fx3ijUYEjHjDUoQ/viewform&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h4 id="resa">ReSA&lt;/h4>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Website: &lt;a href="https://www.researchsoft.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://www.researchsoft.org/&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Sign up for the newsletter: &lt;a href="https://www.researchsoft.org/news/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://www.researchsoft.org/news/&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The &lt;a href="https://ogyaqy.clicks.mlsend.com/ty/c/eyJ2Ijoie1wiYVwiOjc3ODEyOSxcImxcIjoxMzM1MDk5NDcxNDA4Njc3OTMsXCJyXCI6MTMzNTA5OTQ4NTg4OTUwNzkzfSIsInMiOiJiMTU2Y2FhYzI3YjQyZjI1In0" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Amsterdam Declaration on Funding Research Software Sustainability&lt;/a>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Become a signatory: &lt;a href="https://adore.software/sign/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://adore.software/sign/&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul></description></item><item><title>Enabling Open Science Through Research Code: Insights from Episode 1 - Conversations with Researchers Who Code</title><link>https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/blog/2024-10-30-eostrc_ep_1/</link><pubDate>Tue, 29 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/blog/2024-10-30-eostrc_ep_1/</guid><description>&lt;p>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="Episode 1 banner" srcset="
/RSE_Asia/blog/2024-10-30-eostrc_ep_1/banner_episode_1_hu3675105232208193727.webp 400w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2024-10-30-eostrc_ep_1/banner_episode_1_hu5767636956491325620.webp 760w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2024-10-30-eostrc_ep_1/banner_episode_1_hu56647646988795859.webp 1200w"
src="https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/RSE_Asia/blog/2024-10-30-eostrc_ep_1/banner_episode_1_hu3675105232208193727.webp"
width="760"
height="608"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/p>
&lt;p>On &lt;strong>October 10, 2024&lt;/strong>, the first episode of the ‘Enabling Open Science Through Research Code’ community conversation took place. The topic for the first episode was ‘Conversations with Researchers Who Code’ focusing on the pivotal role of research software in enabling open science. The event was hosted by &lt;strong>RSSE Africa&lt;/strong> and the &lt;strong>RSE Asia Association.&lt;/strong> It aimed to bring together researchers from various disciplines to share their experiences of coding, collaboration, and the challenges they face as they navigate the world of open science. This episode was a part of the celebration for &lt;strong>International Research Software Engineer (RSE) Day&lt;/strong>, bringing attention to the growing importance of RSEs in research.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="session-overview">&lt;strong>Session Overview&lt;/strong>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The session kicked off with facilitators &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/aneldavanderwalt/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">&lt;strong>Anelda van der Walt&lt;/strong>&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/saranjeet-k-48ab769b/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">&lt;strong>Saranjeet Kaur&lt;/strong>&lt;/a> welcoming participants and introducing the co-facilitators &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/jyoti-bhogal/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">&lt;strong>Jyoti Bhogal&lt;/strong>&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/mireille-grobbelaar/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">&lt;strong>Mireille Grobbelaar&lt;/strong>&lt;/a>. This diverse team set the stage for a lively discussion with four distinguished speakers: &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/biandri-joubert-phd-8270763b/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">&lt;strong>Dr. Biandri Joubert&lt;/strong>&lt;/a>, &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/gauravbhalerao/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">&lt;strong>Dr. Gaurav Bhalerao&lt;/strong>&lt;/a>, &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/razekmh/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">&lt;strong>Mahmoud Abdelrazek&lt;/strong>&lt;/a>&lt;strong>,&lt;/strong> and &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/prasadsutar11/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">&lt;strong>Prasad Sutar&lt;/strong>&lt;/a>. The session had around 30 participants from all across the world.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="introductions--open-science-insights">&lt;strong>Introductions &amp;amp; Open Science Insights&lt;/strong>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>After a warm welcome, the conversation shifted to the core topic: &lt;strong>open science&lt;/strong> and the importance of research software and systems as described in the &lt;strong>UNESCO Open Science Recommendations&lt;/strong>. The facilitators invited the speakers to share their academic backgrounds, work experiences, and current roles, giving the audience a sense of the various pathways that lead them into the world of research software coding.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Some of the key questions posed to the speakers included:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>What did you study, and where?\&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Do you have postgraduate qualifications?\&lt;/li>
&lt;li>What is your current role, and how does coding feature in your work?&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>This introduction provided a backdrop to understand how the speakers’ careers evolved, and how their coding skills were developed to support their research or that of others at the organisation where they work.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="panel-discussion-the-life-of-a-researcher-who-codes">&lt;strong>Panel Discussion: The Life of a Researcher Who Codes&lt;/strong>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The heart of the session was a &lt;strong>panel discussion&lt;/strong> where the speakers delved deeper into the realities of research coding. Some highlights from the discussion include:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Dr. Gaurav Bhalerao&lt;/strong> explained how coding forms an integral part of his day-to-day activities, particularly in structuring large datasets for neuroscience research. He also shared the challenges of balancing coding with research responsibilities.\&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Mahmoud Abdelrazek&lt;/strong> talked about his work in geospatial analysis and how his team collaborates on coding projects. He highlighted the collaborative nature of his work, where coding is not only a personal skill but also a shared responsibility within his research group.\&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Dr. Biandri Joubert&lt;/strong> touched on the challenges of being the sole programmer in her group and how she overcomes the feeling of isolation by participating in coding communities and seeking support from platforms like the &lt;strong>Carpentries&lt;/strong>.\&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Prasad Sutar&lt;/strong> discussed his experience with developing software that is used by others and the importance of ensuring that his coding practices align with both the research objectives and software quality standards.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>The panel also explored whether all researchers should learn to code. They agreed that even if a researcher doesn’t need to code regularly, learning basic coding concepts is valuable. This foundational knowledge enables researchers to read and understand code at a high level, helping them grasp the algorithms or logic applied to address specific problem statements. A valuable analogy, comparing coding to medical training was suggested during the meetup. Just as it’s beneficial for everyone to learn basic first-aid, it’s useful for researchers to grasp fundamental coding concepts. Some may advance to become paramedics, equivalent to those using coding more regularly, while a few specialize deeply - similar to neurosurgeons or expert programmers. What are your thoughts? Should coding become a core skill for all researchers, or is it more practical to foster collaboration with coding specialists when needed?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The panel also explored topics like the amount of time spent coding, the collaborative nature of research software projects, and the availability of support and training for researchers.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="learning-and-community-support">&lt;strong>Learning and Community Support&lt;/strong>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>An essential part of the discussion revolved around the resources and communities that help researchers improve their coding skills. &lt;strong>Dr. Gaurav Bhalerao&lt;/strong> recommended resources such as &lt;strong>Carpentries lessons&lt;/strong> and online coding tutorials like &lt;strong>p5.js&lt;/strong> for those starting out. The speakers emphasized the importance of continuous learning and staying connected with the global community through platforms like &lt;strong>RLadies&lt;/strong>, &lt;strong>Quarto&lt;/strong>, and others. To know about more resources please see the section &lt;strong>Resources and Links&lt;/strong>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="qa-and-wrap-up">&lt;strong>Q&amp;amp;A and Wrap-Up&lt;/strong>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The session concluded with a &lt;strong>Q&amp;amp;A&lt;/strong> where participants posed questions about the pain points of learning to code, transitioning into a coding role from other fields, and how to stay updated with coding trends while maintaining research quality. One insightful comment came from &lt;strong>Dr. Biandri Joubert&lt;/strong>, who emphasized that code that runs doesn’t always mean it’s correct, highlighting the critical need for combining coding skills with sound statistical knowledge.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The facilitators wrapped up the event by sharing &lt;strong>resources from partners&lt;/strong>, including RSSE Africa, RSE Asia, AREN, and ReSA, all of which provide platforms for collaboration, learning, and advocacy for the Research Software Engineering community.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="resources-and-links">&lt;strong>Resources and Links&lt;/strong>&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>To access the wealth of resources shared in the session, visit our collection at &lt;a href="https://zenodo.org/records/13946139" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Zenodo&lt;/a>.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>For those who missed this enlightening conversation, a &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=UmSHhDVRGig" target="_blank" rel="noopener">recording of Episode 1&lt;/a> is available on the &lt;strong>RSSE Africa website&lt;/strong>. Please remember to &lt;a href="https://us06web.zoom.us/meeting/register/tZcpcu-ppjstGNJwEt1aKRjR6r2aC7Q4qE9Y#/registration" target="_blank" rel="noopener">register for &lt;strong>Episode 2&lt;/strong>&lt;/a> of the series. The conversation continues, highlighting the essential role of research software engineering in advancing open science globally.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h3 id="learn-more-about-us">&lt;strong>Learn More About Us&lt;/strong>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>For more information and to join upcoming events, visit:&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="rsse-africa">RSSE Africa&lt;/h4>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Website: &lt;a href="https://rsse.africa" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://rsse.africa&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Sign up for our newsletter: &lt;a href="https://talarify.us14.list-manage.com/subscribe?u=35d5db26d3b108b9ef9b9ac43&amp;amp;id=55e9f5a692" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://talarify.us14.list-manage.com/subscribe?u=35d5db26d3b108b9ef9b9ac43&amp;id=55e9f5a692&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Join our LinkedIn group, where you can also share information with the broader community: &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/groups/12903402/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://www.linkedin.com/groups/12903402/&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h4 id="rse-asia">RSE Asia&lt;/h4>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Website: &lt;a href="https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>For the latest news, events, activities, and opportunities, follow us on our &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/company/rse-asia-association/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">LinkedIn page&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>To join the RSE Asia community, please fill out our short &lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/forms/d/1XSxDaTJzcNyGeDYXyJNVg1TDCo7un18PLFNiK6_jL2g/edit" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Community Membership Form&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h4 id="aren">AREN&lt;/h4>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Website: &lt;a href="https://africanrn.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://africanrn.org/&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Sign up: &lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLSeeFkD5A4D9l6ncQWjKBiI-GqBOzL-JMe7Fx3ijUYEjHjDUoQ/viewform" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLSeeFkD5A4D9l6ncQWjKBiI-GqBOzL-JMe7Fx3ijUYEjHjDUoQ/viewform&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h4 id="resa">ReSA&lt;/h4>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Website: &lt;a href="https://www.researchsoft.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://www.researchsoft.org/&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Sign up for the newsletter: &lt;a href="https://www.researchsoft.org/news/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://www.researchsoft.org/news/&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The &lt;a href="https://ogyaqy.clicks.mlsend.com/ty/c/eyJ2Ijoie1wiYVwiOjc3ODEyOSxcImxcIjoxMzM1MDk5NDcxNDA4Njc3OTMsXCJyXCI6MTMzNTA5OTQ4NTg4OTUwNzkzfSIsInMiOiJiMTU2Y2FhYzI3YjQyZjI1In0" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Amsterdam Declaration on Funding Research Software Sustainability&lt;/a>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Become a signatory: &lt;a href="https://adore.software/sign/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://adore.software/sign/&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul></description></item><item><title>Insights from My Experience at PyCon India 2024</title><link>https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/blog/2024-10-26_pycon_india_2024/</link><pubDate>Sat, 26 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/blog/2024-10-26_pycon_india_2024/</guid><description>&lt;p>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="Jyoti Bhogal with the PyCon India 2024 Banner" srcset="
/RSE_Asia/blog/2024-10-26_pycon_india_2024/cover_image_Jyoti_conf_banner_hu4533281636997668804.webp 400w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2024-10-26_pycon_india_2024/cover_image_Jyoti_conf_banner_hu17244280389917822082.webp 760w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2024-10-26_pycon_india_2024/cover_image_Jyoti_conf_banner_hu17295497999774588961.webp 1200w"
src="https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/RSE_Asia/blog/2024-10-26_pycon_india_2024/cover_image_Jyoti_conf_banner_hu4533281636997668804.webp"
width="760"
height="701"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="overview">Overview&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The PyCon India 2024 conference, held from September 20-23 at the NIMHANS Convention Center in Bengaluru, brought together a vibrant mix of sessions designed for learning, engagement, and networking. I experienced a diverse lineup, including keynotes, technical talks, hands-on workshops, lightning talks, poster sessions, and open forums (birds of feather (BoF) sessions). Sponsor stalls added to the excitement, and the open spaces allowed for spontaneous interactions, adding to the conference&amp;rsquo;s lively atmosphere. Celebrating its 15th anniversary this year, PyCon India 2024 marked my second time attending, following my first experience at PyCon India 2023 in Hyderabad.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="lightning-talks">Lightning Talks&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>I had the opportunity to present a Lightning Talk titled &lt;em>&amp;ldquo;Accelerating India&amp;rsquo;s Open Science Journey with Python.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em> In my session, I introduced the audience to the concept of open science, highlighting its importance for India, exploring its four foundational pillars, and demonstrating how Python plays a vital role in advancing open science efforts. The talk was well-received, and you can view the slides on &lt;a href="https://zenodo.org/records/13826028" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Zenodo&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="My Lightning Talk" srcset="
/RSE_Asia/blog/2024-10-26_pycon_india_2024/lightning_talk_collage_hu15859592698995382157.webp 400w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2024-10-26_pycon_india_2024/lightning_talk_collage_hu10090254969128491612.webp 760w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2024-10-26_pycon_india_2024/lightning_talk_collage_hu15857847507574625132.webp 1200w"
src="https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/RSE_Asia/blog/2024-10-26_pycon_india_2024/lightning_talk_collage_hu15859592698995382157.webp"
width="760"
height="361"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Click below to view video:&lt;/p>
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/lX896C6QUsE?si=3RwkwLRfNdqWATzb&amp;amp;start=1060" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen>&lt;/iframe>
&lt;h2 id="keynotes">Keynotes&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The conference featured four insightful keynotes:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://kovidgoyal.net/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Kovid Goyal&lt;/a> presented &lt;em>&amp;ldquo;Making Python Programs Fast,&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em> where he shared in-depth techniques to optimize Python performance using C language.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/usha-rengaraju-b570b7a2/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Usha Rengaraju&lt;/a> spoke on &lt;em>&amp;ldquo;AI for Autism,&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em> shedding light on neurodiversity and the potential of AI in autism research.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/mars-lee/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Mars Bar Lee&lt;/a> explored &lt;em>&amp;ldquo;How Open-Source Opened My Opportunities,&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em> highlighting how contributions to open-source projects can extend beyond code, such as her technical illustrations for NumPy.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/dontusethiscode/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">James Powell&lt;/a> delivered a creative talk, &lt;em>&amp;ldquo;How Many Oranges?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>Each keynote brought valuable perspectives, and Mars Bar Lee’s emphasis on non-code contributions was particularly interesting. I got to meet Mars in-person, after having met online previously for a workshop on importance of alt text with images for improving digital accessibility.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="L-R: Mars, Unicorn, me, and NumPy comics" srcset="
/RSE_Asia/blog/2024-10-26_pycon_india_2024/Mars_Jyoti_Unicorn_NumPy_Comics_hu7434170445446112914.webp 400w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2024-10-26_pycon_india_2024/Mars_Jyoti_Unicorn_NumPy_Comics_hu9277460117172359375.webp 760w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2024-10-26_pycon_india_2024/Mars_Jyoti_Unicorn_NumPy_Comics_hu3108070987124473988.webp 1200w"
src="https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/RSE_Asia/blog/2024-10-26_pycon_india_2024/Mars_Jyoti_Unicorn_NumPy_Comics_hu7434170445446112914.webp"
width="760"
height="429"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="workshops">Workshops&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The first day had 3-hour workshops going on in three tracks. I attended two immersive workshops:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Chat with Tables: Developing Q&amp;amp;A system on Tabular data using Code Generative LLMs by &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/abhijeet-kumar-1aa8b0138/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Abhijeet Kumar&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Abhijeet conducted a workshop about Generative AI powered by Large Language Models (LLMs) that are revolutionizing text, image, and video generation, as well as coding through enterprise solutions like GitHub Copilot, Google’s Gemini Code Assist, IBM’s Watsonx, and Amazon’s Q Developer. Abhijeet&amp;rsquo;s workshop focused on leveraging code-generating LLMs to enable non-technical users to generate Python code by using natural language queries, bridging the gap for business users who lack programming skills but need quick data insights. This solution is valuable for business users who often require ad-hoc analysis of tabular data but rely heavily on data teams. Abhijeet demonstrated a workflow to query tabular data, generate insights from CSVs, and enhance natural language querying (NLQ) through techniques like few-shot prompting, pruning, and validation. Additionally, the session included setting up a streamlined process for building Q&amp;amp;A systems for tabular data and creating a Streamlit app, making data insights more accessible to non-technical analysts.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>From Zero to Backend Hero: Creating Full-Featured Apps with FastAPI by &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/vivek-keshore/?original_referer=https%3A%2F%2Fwww%2Egoogle%2Ecom%2F&amp;amp;originalSubdomain=in" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Vivek Keshore&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Vivek started by interacting with the audience to gather basic information like what an API is, the different types of APIs, and the various types of calls. Vivek discussed the benefits of using FastAPI. He went on to discuss database design. Vivek discussed about implementation of Pydantic models and the development of user management APIs.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;h2 id="pyladies-luncheon">PyLadies Luncheon&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The PyLadies Luncheon was a personal highlight during the conference. Women attendees gathered to share their experiences, openly discussing the challenges they face related to diversity and inclusivity in their workplaces and how they’ve overcome these obstacles over time. Hearing these stories and learning about the resilience and strategies of others was truly inspiring and energizing for me.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="sponsor-stalls">Sponsor Stalls&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The conference featured several sponsor stalls, and one that stood out to me was the &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/company/npci/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">National Payments Corporation of India (NPCI)&lt;/a>, an umbrella organization for retail payments and settlement systems in India. I was intrigued to learn how their payments ecosystem is entirely open-source, with data storage managed on-premises instead of on Cloud platforms. Additionally, they introduced me to UPI payments that can be made via phone call or SMS, allowing transactions without an internet connection.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="devsprints">DevSprints&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The DevSprint was a one-day event featuring around 20 different projects. The day began with core contributors providing an overview of their respective projects, allowing participants to choose any project they were interested in contributing to. Among the various projects, I found myself particularly drawn to Django and NumPy.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I opted to join the &lt;a href="https://github.com/numpy/numpy" target="_blank" rel="noopener">NumPy&lt;/a> DevSprint, facilitated by technical illustrator Mars Bar Lee and NumPy core contributor &lt;a href="https://github.com/seberg" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Sebastian Berg&lt;/a>. They introduced all the contributors to the NumPy project, outlining various ways to engage with the community through community calls, mailing lists, and comics, as well as how to contribute effectively. If you&amp;rsquo;re interested in contributing to NumPy, you can refer to the &lt;a href="https://github.com/numpy/numpy/blob/main/CONTRIBUTING.rst" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Contributing Guidelines&lt;/a> for more information.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I had the opportunity to attend an open session led by &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/saptaks/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Saptak S.&lt;/a>, where participants discussed the nuances of digital accessibility, particularly in website development. The discussion covered essential points such as ensuring adequate contrast between text and background colors, structuring headings (H1, H2, H3, etc.) correctly, and guidelines for including appropriate details in the alt text for images. I discovered several valuable online resources to check and test webpage accessibility, including:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.a11yproject.com/checklist/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">A11y Project&lt;/a>: A checklist for assessing accessibility levels.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.deque.com/axe/devtools/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">axe DevTools&lt;/a>: A tool that evaluates whether a website complies with accessibility guidelines, available as an extension for Chrome, Firefox, and MS Edge browsers.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://wave.webaim.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">WAVE&lt;/a>: A tool that highlights areas of a website that are well or poorly designed regarding accessibility. WAVE also offers extensions for Chrome, Firefox, and MS Edge browsers.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.buttoncheatsheet.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">The Button Cheat Sheet&lt;/a>: A resource to determine if buttons on a website&amp;rsquo;s UI are designed effectively.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://webaim.org/projects/million/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">The WebAIM Million&lt;/a>: The 2024 report on the accessibility of the top 1,000,000 home pages.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>We discussed key considerations for developers when creating digitally accessible web pages. For instance, keyboard navigation is crucial for individuals with visual impairments or otherwise while working with a document by using only the keyboard, necessitating a logical heading structure (e.g., H1 followed by H2, and so on). It’s important to avoid jumping from say, H1 to H4, as this can confuse users.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In terms of coding practices, developers should specify the document language by adding the ‘lang’ attribute. This helps indicate which programming language is being used for different sections of the website. Additionally, tools like &lt;a href="https://www.freedomscientific.com/products/software/jaws/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">JAWS&lt;/a> provide voice assistance to help developers ensure accessibility standards are met.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>During Continuous Integration (CI), it’s essential for developers to incorporate these accessibility guidelines into their workflows.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Saptak also recommended several excellent learning resources, such as &lt;a href="https://adrianroselli.com/tag/accessibility" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Adrian Roselli’s&lt;/a> articles on accessibility issues, conference talks from experts in digital accessibility, and a helpful site for determining whether to use a carousel post: &lt;a href="https://shouldiuseacarousel.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Should I Use a Carousel?&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The PyCon India 2024 concluded with the DevSprints, marking an incredibly immersive learning experience for me. The Closing Ceremony featured two beat-box artists who entertained us, adding a refreshing twist to the event. I also had the pleasure of meeting &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/tanvi-agarwal-sillystrokes/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Tanvi Agarwal&lt;/a>, a digital illustrator who provides live transcription of talks, which I found truly inspiring. A big thank you to the entire PyCon India volunteer organizing team for once again delivering a fantastic conference!&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h3 id="learn-more-about-us">&lt;strong>Learn More About Us&lt;/strong>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>For more information and to join upcoming events, visit:&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="rse-asia">RSE Asia&lt;/h4>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Website: &lt;a href="https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>For the latest news, events, activities, and opportunities, follow us on our &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/company/rse-asia-association/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">LinkedIn page&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>To join the RSE Asia community, please fill out our short &lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/forms/d/1XSxDaTJzcNyGeDYXyJNVg1TDCo7un18PLFNiK6_jL2g/edit" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Community Membership Form&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul></description></item><item><title>My experience note of RSE Asia Australia Unconference 2022</title><link>https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/blog/2022-10-01-rseaaexp22/</link><pubDate>Fri, 18 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/blog/2022-10-01-rseaaexp22/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="what-is-the-rseaa-unconference">What is the RSEAA Unconference?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>An unconference is a conference which is driven by the participants who engage in active discussions with optionally having presentations too.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The RSEAA 2022 unconference had a mixed style of regular conference and unconference.
The regular style part had three keynote and a panel discussion.
Recordings of the keynotes and panel discussion are available on YouTube.&lt;/p>
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/-0OAhgHuJI4" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen>&lt;/iframe>
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Q4fR1RXydLw" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen>&lt;/iframe>
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/lN1GICnbohI" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen>&lt;/iframe>
&lt;p>In addition, it should be noted that the summary report is published at DOI (figshare) below.
(It&amp;rsquo;s great, so please take a look.)&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma">&lt;code class="language-fallback" data-lang="fallback">&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">Mosbergen, Rowland (2022): Research Software Engineer Asia Australia Unconference Summary Report. figshare. Online resource. https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.21201989.v2
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;h2 id="thoughts-on-the-keynotes">Thoughts on the keynotes&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>RSEAA 2022 had three keynotes.
I watched the Mars&amp;rsquo;s and Anne&amp;rsquo;s keynotes live.
(I was unable to watch Jess&amp;rsquo;s keynote live.)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Here are my thoughts on Mars&amp;rsquo;s and Anne&amp;rsquo;s keynote.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="mars-lee">Mars Lee&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://github.com/MarsBarLee" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Mars&lt;/a> is a technical illustrator at &lt;a href="https://quansight.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Quansight&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Mars has a slightly different career path for RSE, and she introduced it in the keynote.
I think Mars&amp;rsquo; talk was a great talk that helped improve inclusivity of the RSE community.
You can check the slides in &lt;a href="https://github.com/MarsBarLee/2022-RSE-Asia-Australia-Unconference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">this GitHub repo&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/EPHJhLgbK5w" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen>&lt;/iframe>
&lt;h3 id="anne-steele">Anne Steele&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.aleesteele.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Anne&lt;/a> is a community manager of &lt;a href="https://the-turing-way.netlify.app/welcome" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the Turing Way&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Anne&amp;rsquo;s talk covered her career history, what she&amp;rsquo;s learned through her career and the projects she&amp;rsquo;s working on.
Anne introduced the objectives of equality, diversity and inclusion in improving reproducibility and openness of research.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In Japan, where I live, there is no Community Manager for Open Science like Anne.
So it was an exciting opportunity for me to know about this role.&lt;/p>
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/VKH8RuSCq4c" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen>&lt;/iframe>
&lt;h2 id="about-the-unconference-part">About the &amp;ldquo;Unconference&amp;rdquo; part&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The parts other than the keynote were held in an &amp;ldquo;Unconference&amp;rdquo; format.
Here are the themes of the discussion that took place there.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="Within the RSEAA 2022 Zoom Event, we were able to enter and leave rooms that were divided into different themes for the unconference." srcset="
/RSE_Asia/blog/2022-10-01-rseaaexp22/zoomevent_hu14732178549151147323.webp 400w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2022-10-01-rseaaexp22/zoomevent_hu3670003114741123384.webp 760w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2022-10-01-rseaaexp22/zoomevent_hu6055608418205500602.webp 1200w"
src="https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/RSE_Asia/blog/2022-10-01-rseaaexp22/zoomevent_hu14732178549151147323.webp"
width="760"
height="497"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Computational Reproducibility&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Quantify RSE outputs&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Benchmarking domain-specific research workflow solutions at an international level&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Hosting research software&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Bridging the gap between biologists and programmers&lt;/li>
&lt;li>What exactly does the most senior RSE look like?&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Questions to ask your supervisor at your RSE performance review&lt;/li>
&lt;li>What would a secure RSE position look like?&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Let&amp;rsquo;s discuss employment realities, as a student, as a grad, as a postgrad, as an ECR&lt;/li>
&lt;li>RSE Silos&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Software as first-class outputs&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Justifying maintenance work&lt;/li>
&lt;li>A Web Platform for RSEs&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Actionable Items 1 - Community Building&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Actionable Items 2 - Peer programming and collaboration&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>What are your thoughts on each of the above themes?
Probably all of them are exactly what you(==RSE) want to discuss with someone.
I was very impressed to learn that there are places (communities) in the world where people can discuss these themes.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="impressions-about-the-rseaa-accessibility-and-a-call-for-non-english-speaking-rses-participation">&amp;ldquo;Impressions about the RSEAA accessibility&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;a call for non-English-speaking RSEs participation&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>RSEAA 2022 had a great attention to accessibility.
I am Japanese and I am not good at English.
However, RSEAA 2022 had Zoom&amp;rsquo;s Live Transcription feature, so I had no trouble listening to English.
Many Japanese can read English, but cannot listen or speak.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>RSEAA 2022 was well prepared on accessibility and &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/DogGeneticsLLC" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Liz Hare&lt;/a> provided a &lt;a href="https://rse-aunz.github.io/RSEAUNZAccessibility.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">high level accessibility report for the conference&lt;/a>.
If you&amp;rsquo;re avoiding joining the RSE community because you&amp;rsquo;re not good at English, don&amp;rsquo;t be afraid.
The RSE community is a community that cares about inclusiveness.
Please feel free to join to the RSE community!&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="further-information-about-rse-and-my-gratitude-for-rseaa-organizaers">Further information about RSE and my gratitude for RSEAA organizaers&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>If you are interested in the RSE community, please take a look at &lt;a href="https://github.com/softwaresaved/international-survey-2022" target="_blank" rel="noopener">International RSE Survey 2022&lt;/a>.
It was released during this RSEAA 2022.
I think that looking at the survey results will help us understand the current situation and think about the future.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Finally, I would like to thank all the organizers for running RSEAA 2022.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h3 id="learn-more-about-us">&lt;strong>Learn More About Us&lt;/strong>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>For more information and to join upcoming events, visit:&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="rse-asia">RSE Asia&lt;/h4>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Website: &lt;a href="https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>For the latest news, events, activities, and opportunities, follow us on our &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/company/rse-asia-association/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">LinkedIn page&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>To join the RSE Asia community, please fill out our short &lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/forms/d/1XSxDaTJzcNyGeDYXyJNVg1TDCo7un18PLFNiK6_jL2g/edit" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Community Membership Form&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul></description></item><item><title>My Experience of Participating in Open Life Science Cohort-5</title><link>https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/blog/2022-10-07-ols5exp22/</link><pubDate>Wed, 10 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/blog/2022-10-07-ols5exp22/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>Click below for the slide.&lt;/em>
&lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1aYyBzvDkGMRzl1pMt0RJ4de772t-SwzGyXgmMkHrUWY/edit#slide=id.p" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1aYyBzvDkGMRzl1pMt0RJ4de772t-SwzGyXgmMkHrUWY/edit#slide=id.p&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;a href="`r rmarkdown::metadata$url`">
```{r}
knitr::include_graphics("preview.png")
```
&lt;/a>
&lt;h2 id="project-title-and-motivation">Project Title and Motivation&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>In the OLS-5 cohort, I got the opportunity to work on my project titled &amp;lsquo;Building Pathways for Onboarding to Research Software Engineering (RSE) Asia Association and Adoption of Code of Conduct&amp;rsquo;. My mentor for the program was &lt;a href="https://malvikasharan.github.io/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Malvika Sharan&lt;/a>. There are several incidents when people want to contribute in a community activity, but the community does not have a well-defined path that will help a new person contribute. This motivated me to work on building pathways for new members to join the RSE Asia Association.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="the-backstory">The Backstory&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The inception of RSE Asia Association goes back to September 2021, when our idea of starting it got the support of the experts from the OLS-4 cohort. Back then we started off with a basic logo. We had set up the entire digital structure need to run the community. During cohort 5, we updated the logo.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="milestones-the-rse-asia-association-crossed-during-ols-5">Milestones the RSE Asia Association Crossed During OLS-5&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Let&amp;rsquo;s have a look at the milestones in the journey that RSE Asia Association went through while OLS-5.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="milestone-1">Milestone 1&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The selection into OLS-5 itself was a milestone. Following which, we started discussions around how to get our Association registered.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We wanted to register ourselves as an NGO. With the guidance from my mentor Malvika, I read several articles. I found out about the different types of NGOs that function here in India. After careful reading, understanding and discussions with my mentor, we finalized which type of NGO would be best for us to register as. At the moment, the registration is a work in progress.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="milestone-2">Milestone 2&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>When it comes to community work, we had identified that a lot of people are enthusiastic about participating in community work, however many communities face an issue when it comes to a smooth process for people to join them. Hence, we decided to define clear pathways for people to join us, to contribute/learn for a specific time duration.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="milestone-3">Milestone 3&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The RSE Asia Association also got listed as an &amp;lsquo;Observer Association&amp;rsquo; at the International Council of RSE Associations.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="milestone-4">Milestone 4&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>On 8th July 2022, we conducted a workshop, where Isabela Presedo-Floyd and Mars Lee very graciously accepted our invitation to share their knowledge of how alt-texts are written. It was indeed a very exciting and engaging event where people did hands-on work!&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="next-steps">Next steps&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Jyoti would continue with the formalities of getting the association registered legally. Saranjeet and Jyoti are planning to conduct more and more exciting events and workshops.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="staying-connected">Staying connected&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Come have a look at our activities!
We are absolutely active on Twitter. We send out all our updates, reminders and links to various forms via our twitter handle which is @RSE_Asia. Do check out our twitter page, look at our past and upcoming events, DM us to speak your thoughts!&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="special-mentions-and-acknowledgements">Special mentions and acknowledgements&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>We feel very grateful to the OLS team for giving us this chance to grow our RSE Asia Association!
We are extremely thankful to be a part of such a wonderful and supportive community that OLS is!
And our contact details are shown herewith. You can get in touch with us via our twitter handle, our email address.
You can also visit our website, YouTube channel or our GitHub page.
Thank you!!!&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h3 id="learn-more-about-us">&lt;strong>Learn More About Us&lt;/strong>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>For more information and to join upcoming events, visit:&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="rse-asia">RSE Asia&lt;/h4>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Website: &lt;a href="https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>For the latest news, events, activities, and opportunities, follow us on our &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/company/rse-asia-association/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">LinkedIn page&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>To join the RSE Asia community, please fill out our short &lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/forms/d/1XSxDaTJzcNyGeDYXyJNVg1TDCo7un18PLFNiK6_jL2g/edit" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Community Membership Form&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul></description></item><item><title>RSE Asia Australia Unconference 2022 体験記</title><link>https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/blog/2022-10-01-rseaaexp22-ja/</link><pubDate>Wed, 10 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/blog/2022-10-01-rseaaexp22-ja/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="rse-のアンカンファレンスとは何か">RSE のアンカンファレンスとは何か&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>RSE は Research Software Engineer の略称です。
RSEの定義を知るには&lt;a href="https://researchsoftware.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">このリンク&lt;/a>を参照してください。
アンカンファレンス とは参加者同士が主体的に議論するスタイルのカンファレンスのことです。&lt;/p>
&lt;p>RSEAA のアンカンファレンスは、
通常のカンファレンスのようなキーノートスピーカー+パネルディスカッションと、
アンカンファレンスがミックスされたスタイルで開催されました。&lt;/p>
&lt;p>キーノートスピーカーとパネルディスカッションについては録画物をYouTubeで見ることができます。&lt;/p>
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/-0OAhgHuJI4" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen>&lt;/iframe>
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Q4fR1RXydLw" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen>&lt;/iframe>
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/lN1GICnbohI" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen>&lt;/iframe>
&lt;p>また、特筆すべきことにそのサマリーレポートは下記 DOI (figshare)で公開されています。ぜひご覧ください。&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma">&lt;code class="language-fallback" data-lang="fallback">&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">Mosbergen, Rowland (2022): Research Software Engineer Asia Australia Unconference Summary Report. figshare. Online resource. https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.21201989.v2
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;h2 id="キーノートスピーチに関する感想">キーノートスピーチに関する感想&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>RSEAA には3人のキーノートスピーチがありました。
私は Mars と Anne のスピーチをライブで聴講しました。
私は Jess のスピーチは仕事の都合でライブで聞くことはできませんでした。&lt;/p>
&lt;p>ここでは Mars と Anne のキーノートに関する感想を述べます。&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="mars-lee">Mars Lee&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Mars は Quansight のテクニカルイラストレーターです。
Mars は RSE としては少し変わったキャリアパスの持ち主であり、彼女はそれをこのキーノートスピーチで紹介していました。
Mars のトークは、RSEコミュニティの包括性の向上に役立つすばらしいトークだったと思います。&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Mars のスライドは、&lt;a href="https://github.com/MarsBarLee/2022-RSE-Asia-Australia-Unconference" target="_blank" rel="noopener">この GitHub リンク&lt;/a>
にあります。&lt;/p>
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/EPHJhLgbK5w" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen>&lt;/iframe>
&lt;h3 id="anne-steele">Anne Steele&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Anne は &lt;a href="https://the-turing-way.netlify.app/welcome" target="_blank" rel="noopener">The Turing Way&lt;/a> のコミュニティマネージャーです。
Anne のトークは彼女のキャリアの歴史、彼女が学んできたこと、そして今関わっているプロジェクトを紹介するものでした。
Anne は主に The Turing Way を通して再現性の改善や研究のオープン化において、平等、多様性、包括性といった目的をどのように実現しようとしているかを説明していました。
日本では Anne のようなオープンサイエンスコミュニティのためのコミュニティマネージャーはいません。
そのため、それは貴重な機会でした。&lt;/p>
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/VKH8RuSCq4c" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen>&lt;/iframe>
&lt;h2 id="アンカンファレンスのパートについて">アンカンファレンスのパートについて&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>キーノート以外のパートはアンカンファレンス形式で行われました。
ここではそこで行われた議論のテーマを箇条書きします。&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="Zoom Events 内では、アンカンファレンスのテーマ毎に分かれた部屋を選択して入退出できました" srcset="
/RSE_Asia/blog/2022-10-01-rseaaexp22-ja/zoomevent_hu14732178549151147323.webp 400w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2022-10-01-rseaaexp22-ja/zoomevent_hu3670003114741123384.webp 760w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2022-10-01-rseaaexp22-ja/zoomevent_hu6055608418205500602.webp 1200w"
src="https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/RSE_Asia/blog/2022-10-01-rseaaexp22-ja/zoomevent_hu14732178549151147323.webp"
width="760"
height="497"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>計算の再現性について (Computational Reproducibility)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>RSE の成果の定量化について (Quantify RSE outputs)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>国際レベルでのドメイン固有の研究ワークフローソリューションのベンチマーク (Benchmarking domain-specific research workflow solutions at an international level)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>研究ソフトウェアのホスティングについて (Hosting research software)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Biologists と Programmers のギャップを埋めることについて (#BridgingTheGap between #Biologists and #Programmers)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>最上級の RSE とは正確にはどのようなものか? (What exactly does the most senior RSE look like?)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>RSE のパフォーマンスのレビューで上司に尋ねる質問 (Questions to ask your supervisor at your RSE performance review)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>安全な RSE ポジションとはどのようなものか? (What would a secure RSE position look like?)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>学生として、卒業生として、大学院生として、ECR [注: Early Career Researcher] として、雇用の現実について話し合おう (Let&amp;rsquo;s discuss employment realities, as a student, as a grad, as a postgrad, as an ECR)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>RSE の複数のサイロについて [注: サイロとはアプリやシステムが孤立し情報が連携されていないことを言います] (RSE Silos)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>一流のアウトプットとしてのソフトウェアについて (Software as first-class outputs)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>保守作業を正当化することについて [注: 研究ソフトウェア業界では保守に対する評価はされません] (Justifying maintenance work)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>RSE 達のためのウェブプラットフォームについて (A Web Platform for RSEs)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>実行可能なアイテム1 - コミュニティの構築 (Actionable Items1 - Community Building)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>実行可能なアイテム2 - Peer programming [注: 何らかの環境を複数人で共有してプログラミングすること] とコラボレーション (Actionable Items2 - Peer programming and collaboration)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>上記の各テーマを見て、あなたはどう思われましたか？
おそらくどれも普段疑問に感じている、しかし身近に相談する人がいない、と思うことではないでしょうか？
それはまさに私も同じであり、このアンカンファレンスに参加して
「こういったテーマを議論できる場(コミュニティ)が世界には存在するのだ」ということを知り、感銘を受けました。&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="アクセシビリティに関する印象と非英語圏の-rse-達への参加の呼びかけ">アクセシビリティに関する印象と、非英語圏の RSE 達への参加の呼びかけ&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>RSEAA はアクセシビリティに対する配慮が優れていました。
私は日本人であり英語が得意ではありません。
ですが RSEAA では Zoom の live transcription 機能が有効化されており、英語を聞きとることについては不自由がありませんでした。
日本人の多くはリーディングはできますが、リスニングとスピーキングができません。&lt;/p>
&lt;p>RSEAA はアクセシビリティについて十分に準備を整えており、&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/DogGeneticsLLC" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Liz Hare&lt;/a> は RSEAA のために&lt;a href="%28https://rse-aunz.github.io/2022-Asia-Australia-unconference/#:~:text=Accessibility%20and%20Inclusivity%29">ハイレベルなアクセシビリティレポート&lt;/a>を提供しています。&lt;/p>
&lt;p>英語が苦手で RSE コミュニティへの参加を避けている場合でも、恐れる必要はありません。
RSE コミュニティは、包括性を重視するコミュニティです。
お気軽に RSE コミュニティに参加してください !&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="rse-についてのさらなる情報と-rseaa-のオーガナイザーへの感謝">RSE についてのさらなる情報と RSEAA のオーガナイザーへの感謝&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>ここまで読んでいただいて RSE コミュニティに興味を持っていただいた方は
&lt;a href="https://github.com/softwaresaved/international-survey-2022" target="_blank" rel="noopener">International RSE Survey 2022&lt;/a>
をぜひご覧ください。
それはこの RSEAA の期間中に公開されたばかりです。
そのサーベイ結果を見ることは現状把握と今後を考えるのに役立つと思います。&lt;/p>
&lt;p>最後に、RSEAA を運営してくださった主催者の皆様に感謝いたします。&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h3 id="learn-more-about-us">&lt;strong>Learn More About Us&lt;/strong>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>For more information and to join upcoming events, visit:&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="rse-asia">RSE Asia&lt;/h4>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Website: &lt;a href="https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>For the latest news, events, activities, and opportunities, follow us on our &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/company/rse-asia-association/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">LinkedIn page&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>To join the RSE Asia community, please fill out our short &lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/forms/d/1XSxDaTJzcNyGeDYXyJNVg1TDCo7un18PLFNiK6_jL2g/edit" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Community Membership Form&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul></description></item><item><title>Can National Research and Education Networks be a focal point for Research Software Engineers in some regions?</title><link>https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-06-28-nren_rse/</link><pubDate>Mon, 17 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-06-28-nren_rse/</guid><description>&lt;p>This blog explores my thoughts on the potential role of &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National_research_and_education_network" target="_blank" rel="noopener">National Research and Education Networks (NRENs)&lt;/a> in promoting the growth of a Research Software Engineering (RSE) community in Asia-Pacific. The significance of this lies in the fact that NRENs have not traditionally been significantly involved in supporting RSE groups in other regions.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As I delved deeper into this topic, I learned that NRENs are specialised internet service providers designed to cater to the needs of research and education sectors in a particular region or country. These networks typically feature high-speed backbone connectivity and may provide dedicated channels for individual research initiatives. In the Asia-Pacific region, the &lt;a href="https://apan.net" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Asia Pacific Advanced Network (APAN)&lt;/a> is the international partnership of the NRENs that provides both domestic and international high-speed network connectivity.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="rse-asia-at-apan">RSE Asia at APAN&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>My interest in this topic grew during my participation in the &lt;a href="https://society-rse.org/events/pilot-mentoring-programme/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Society of RSE pilot mentoring programme&lt;/a>, where my mentor, &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/michelledbarker/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Michelle Barker&lt;/a>, introduced me to APAN. As a result, I attended the &lt;a href="https://apan53.apan.net" target="_blank" rel="noopener">53rd APAN meeting (APAN53)&lt;/a>, which was held virtually from March 7th to 11th, 2022.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>At APAN53, I contributed to a panel discussion entitled &amp;ldquo;Accelerating the paradigm shift towards Open Science and Data Sharing in pandemic times and beyond&amp;rdquo; and presented the &lt;a href="https://zenodo.org/record/7698570#.ZDV0Hi8Rp-U" target="_blank" rel="noopener">advancements of the RSE Asia Association&lt;/a>. Additionally, I shared the &lt;a href="https://zenodo.org/record/7698591#.ZDV0Uy8Rp-U" target="_blank" rel="noopener">narratives from RSE Asia Association&lt;/a> at the workshop session titled &amp;ldquo;Growing research software initiatives and communities in the Asia Pacific.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>However, it was at the &lt;a href="https://apan55.apan.net/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">55th Asia Pacific Advanced Network (APAN55)&lt;/a> meeting in Kathmandu, Nepal, where I had the opportunity to attend as a &lt;a href="http://apan.net/fellowship/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">APAN55 Fellow&lt;/a>, that I gained more knowledge about the &lt;a href="#national-research-and-education-networks-in-asia">NRENs in Asia&lt;/a>. The &lt;a href="https://www.nren.net.np" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Nepal NREN&lt;/a> played an essential role in organising and hosting the event this year, and similarly, the &lt;a href="https://www.ac.lk" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Lanka Education and Research Network (LEARN)&lt;/a>, the Sri Lankan NREN, will be hosting and organising the upcoming APAN56 meeting.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="national-research-and-education-networks-in-asia">National Research and Education Networks in Asia&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Afghanistan: Afghanistan NREN (AfgREN)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Bangladesh: &lt;a href="https://www.bdren.net.bd" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Bangladesh NREN (BdREN)&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>China: &lt;a href="https://www.cstcloud.net/cstnet.htm" target="_blank" rel="noopener">China Science and Technology Network (CSTNET)&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>China: &lt;a href="https://www.edu.cn/english/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">China Education and Research Network (CERNET)&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Hong Kong: &lt;a href="https://www.jucc.edu.hk/harnet/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Hong Kong Academic and Research Network (HARNET)&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>India: &lt;a href="https://ernet.in" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Education and Research Network of India (ERNET)&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>India: &lt;a href="https://nkn.gov.in/en/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">National Knowledge Network (NKN) India&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Indonesia: &lt;a href="https://idren.id" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Indonesia Research and Education Network (IdREN)&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Japan: &lt;a href="https://www.sinet.ad.jp/en/aboutsinet-en" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Science Information Network (SINET) Japan&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Korea: &lt;a href="https://www.koren.kr/eng/index.asp" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Korea Advanced Research Network (KOREN)&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Korea: &lt;a href="https://www.kreonet.net/eng/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Korea Research Environment Open Network (KREONET)&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Malaysia: &lt;a href="https://www.myren.net.my" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Malaysian Research and Education Network (MyREN)&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Nepal: &lt;a href="https://www.nren.net.np" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Nepal Research and Education Network (NREN)&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Pakistan: &lt;a href="https://pern.edu.pk" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Pakistan Education and Research Network (PERN)&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Philippines: &lt;a href="https://asti.dost.gov.ph/projects/preginet/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Philippine Research , Education and Government Information Network (PREGINET)&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Singapore: &lt;a href="https://www.singaren.net.sg" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Singapore Advanced Research and Education Network (SingAREN)&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Sri Lanka: &lt;a href="https://www.ac.lk" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Lanka Education and Research Network (LEARN)&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Taiwan: &lt;a href="https://www.twaren.net/english/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Taiwan Advanced Research and Education Network (TWAREN)&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Thailand: &lt;a href="https://www.uni.net.th" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Thailand Education and Research Network (UniNet)&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Vietnam: &lt;a href="https://www.vista.gov.vn/vinaren.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Vietnam Research and Education Network (VinaREN)&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>At APAN55, I presented the &lt;a href="https://zenodo.org/record/7817687" target="_blank" rel="noopener">&amp;ldquo;RSE Asia Association: Journey and Future Plans&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a> at the “Open and Sharing Data Working Group (OSDWG): Asia Pacific Open-Sharing Data and NRENs Open Science” session. Additionally, to promote the RSE Asia Association, I shared swag (sponsored by the &lt;a href="https://openlifesci.org" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Open Life Science&lt;/a> programme). During the session, I also organised an activity in which participants were asked to share their ideas on Research Software Engineering (RSEng) as a career path and how open science could benefit researchers globally. I noticed several parallels between the duties and expertise of the staff at NRENs who develop research software infrastructure and those of RSEs while interacting with the attendees.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In a &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/RSE_Asia/status/1635942735948414978?s=20" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Twitter thread&lt;/a>, I compiled responses from APAN55 participants regarding their opinions on RSEng as a profession and a career path. One person from Malaysia responded, &amp;ldquo;I think it&amp;rsquo;s an interesting path to choose especially for people who like to do research and also want to develop software&amp;rdquo;. An attendee from Nepal commented, &amp;ldquo;For me it&amp;rsquo;s a domain of software engineering”, while someone from South Korea observed that software has a significant impact in various domains. They stated that with software being integrated into almost every domain, there is a need for research to enhance its capabilities. Another participant from Nepal mentioned that they believed the role of RSEng to be important and its significance had grown over time. They further stated that the particular requirements of researchers could only be met by specialised software engineers who develop an understanding of the research ecosystem, have knowledge of existing solutions, and are capable of bridging any gaps that may exist. Quoting an attendee from India, &amp;ldquo;Indeed there could be a wonderful career for a software engineer in academia. If they get a rich experience over technology it can help the researchers to facilitate their theory into a workable project or product. Software Engineering could be a backbone where concepts can be transformed into productive algorithms and results can be automated. It can also set up a process path for executing a project. Problem statements can be set up by a software engineer for a group of students and academics.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;img src="APAN55_RSEAsia_Nepal.png" alt="From left to right and top to bottom) Saranjeet's presentation about the RSE Asia Association, RSE Asia Association swags, Twitter thread about the activity. Image credit: Saranjeet Kaur Bhogal"/>
&lt;p>&lt;em>(From left to right and top to bottom) My presentation about the RSE Asia Association, RSE Asia Association swags, Twitter thread about the activity.&lt;/em> &lt;strong>Image credit:&lt;/strong> &lt;a href="mailto:kaur.saranjeet3@gmail.com">Saranjeet Kaur Bhogal&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="call-to-action">Call to Action&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>In general, I have observed that RSEng is gaining recognition in broader conversations about Open Science, Open Source, etc. However, there seems to be a lack of direct attention towards this topic in the Asian region, as mentioned in a report on &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href="https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/blog/2022-10/">Expanding the mapping of the global research software community&lt;/a>.&amp;rdquo; To address this gap, I have been promoting awareness and leading the efforts to focus on RSEng within the APAN network (at APAN53 and APAN55). Given the breadth of the APAN network and NRENs in Asia, they could serve as a great hub for the research software community in the region. If you have any suggestions on how we can leverage NRENs to foster the growth of the RSEng community in Asia, please feel free to &lt;a href="mailto:kaur.saranjeet3@gmail.com">get in touch&lt;/a>. We might be able to submit a panel discussion on this topic at APAN56! Also feel free to share any ideas for other relevant conferences in the Asia-Pacific region.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Acknowledgements:&lt;/strong>
&lt;em>This blog post has benefitted from the suggestions and feedback by &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/michelledbarker/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Michelle Barker&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/pambio/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Paula Andrea Martinez&lt;/a>.&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h3 id="learn-more-about-us">&lt;strong>Learn More About Us&lt;/strong>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>For more information and to join upcoming events, visit:&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="rse-asia">RSE Asia&lt;/h4>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Website: &lt;a href="https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>For the latest news, events, activities, and opportunities, follow us on our &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/company/rse-asia-association/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">LinkedIn page&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>To join the RSE Asia community, please fill out our short &lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/forms/d/1XSxDaTJzcNyGeDYXyJNVg1TDCo7un18PLFNiK6_jL2g/edit" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Community Membership Form&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul></description></item><item><title>Contact</title><link>https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/contact/</link><pubDate>Mon, 24 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/contact/</guid><description/></item><item><title>People</title><link>https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/people/</link><pubDate>Mon, 24 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/people/</guid><description/></item><item><title>OLS team plants a tree dedicated to its cohort-4 in the OLS forest</title><link>https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/post/22-05-11-ols-tree/</link><pubDate>Wed, 11 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/post/22-05-11-ols-tree/</guid><description>&lt;p>RSE Asia was launched as a project in the cohort-4 of the OLS.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The Open Life Science (OLS) team &lt;a href="https://tree-nation.com/trees/view/2880963" target="_blank" rel="noopener">planted a tree dedicated to its cohort-4 in the OLS forest&lt;/a>. RSE Asia was launched as a project in the cohort-4 of the OLS programme.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>RSE Asia featured in the Collaborations Workshop 2022 highlights</title><link>https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/post/22-04-24-cw22-highlights/</link><pubDate>Sun, 24 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/post/22-04-24-cw22-highlights/</guid><description>&lt;p>Proud moment for the RSE Asia community on getting featured in the Collaborations Workshop 2022 highlights.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>RSE Asia got featured in the &lt;a href="https://www.software.ac.uk/blog/2022-04-28-highlights-collaborations-workshop-2022" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Collaborations Workshop 2022 highlights&lt;/a> blogpost by the Software Sustainability Institute.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>An example preprint / working paper</title><link>https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/publication/preprint/</link><pubDate>Sun, 07 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/publication/preprint/</guid><description>&lt;div class="alert alert-note">
&lt;div>
Create your slides in Markdown - click the &lt;em>Slides&lt;/em> button to check out the example.
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>Add the publication&amp;rsquo;s &lt;strong>full text&lt;/strong> or &lt;strong>supplementary notes&lt;/strong> here. You can use rich formatting such as including &lt;a href="https://docs.hugoblox.com/content/writing-markdown-latex/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">code, math, and images&lt;/a>.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title/><link>https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/admin/config.yml</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/admin/config.yml</guid><description/></item></channel></rss>