<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Jyoti Bhogal | RSE Asia Association</title><link>https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/author/jyoti-bhogal/</link><atom:link href="https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/author/jyoti-bhogal/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Jyoti Bhogal</description><generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 02 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/media/icon_hu11734318148517933569.png</url><title>Jyoti Bhogal</title><link>https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/author/jyoti-bhogal/</link></image><item><title>RSE Asia signs its first MoU</title><link>https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-08-04-apan_mou/</link><pubDate>Tue, 02 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-08-04-apan_mou/</guid><description>&lt;p>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="Image: RSE Asia and APAN signing the MoU." srcset="
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-08-04-apan_mou/RSE_Asia_APAN_MoU_hu432188780849466740.webp 400w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-08-04-apan_mou/RSE_Asia_APAN_MoU_hu16565271671934022273.webp 760w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-08-04-apan_mou/RSE_Asia_APAN_MoU_hu9339817199177199870.webp 1200w"
src="https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-08-04-apan_mou/RSE_Asia_APAN_MoU_hu432188780849466740.webp"
width="760"
height="760"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/p>
&lt;p>At the 60th meeting of the &lt;a href="https://apan60.apan.net/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Asia Pacific Advanced Network (APAN60)&lt;/a> in Hong Kong, the RSE Asia Association officially signed its first-ever Memorandum of Understanding (MoU) with the &lt;a href="https://apan.net/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Asia Pacific Advanced Network (APAN)&lt;/a>. At the signing, the RSE Asia Association was represented by our Co-Founder Jyoti Bhogal and the Asia Pacific Advanced Network was represented by the Chair of the APAN Board of Directors, Prof. Dr. Shinji Shimojo.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="what-is-apan">What is APAN?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The Asia Pacific Advanced Network (APAN) is the international partnership of the National Research and Education Networks NRENs connecting communities across the Asia-Pacific region. APAN provides a platform for collaboration, knowledge sharing, and the development of advanced networking technologies to support research and education.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="what-does-this-mou-mean-for-rse-asia">What does this MoU mean for RSE Asia?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>This collaboration marks an exciting step forward for our volunteer-driven community, committed to raising awareness and building capacity in research software engineering (RSE) across Asia. With APAN’s extensive network of research and education stakeholders primarily focused around the Asia-Pacific and RSE Asia’s growing grassroots community, this collaboration opens up new opportunities to support researchers and software engineers alike within the region.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="next-steps">Next steps&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The MoU outlines several key areas of collaboration between RSE Asia and APAN. We’re excited to begin this journey together and look forward to co-developing initiatives that benefit the research software engineering community in Asia!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>To stay updated on what’s next, follow our &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/company/rse-asia-association/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">LinkedIn page&lt;/a>!&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h3 id="learn-more-about-us">&lt;strong>Learn More About Us&lt;/strong>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>For more information and to join upcoming events, visit:&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="rse-asia">RSE Asia&lt;/h4>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Website: &lt;a href="https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>For the latest news, events, activities, and opportunities, follow us on our &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/company/rse-asia-association/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">LinkedIn page&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>To join the RSE Asia community, please fill out our short &lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/forms/d/1XSxDaTJzcNyGeDYXyJNVg1TDCo7un18PLFNiK6_jL2g/edit" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Community Membership Form&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul></description></item><item><title>Halò Scotland! Visiting EPCC in the Edinburgh Sunshine</title><link>https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-05-27_epcc_talk/</link><pubDate>Thu, 29 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-05-27_epcc_talk/</guid><description>&lt;p>As part of my SSI Fellowship project, I was invited to visit &lt;a href="https://www.epcc.ed.ac.uk/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">EPCC at the University of Edinburgh&lt;/a> and give a talk about my work. This was following my participation in the &lt;a href="https://www.software.ac.uk/workshop/collaborations-workshop-2025-cw25" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Collaborations Workshop 2025&lt;/a> organised by the &lt;a href="https://www.software.ac.uk/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Software Sustainability Institute (SSI)&lt;/a> at the &lt;a href="https://www.stir.ac.uk/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">University of Stirling&lt;/a>. I was joined by SSI Fellows &lt;strong>Samantha Wittke&lt;/strong> and &lt;strong>Saranjeet Kaur&lt;/strong>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="Image: (Left to Right) SSI Fellows: Saranjeet Kaur, Jyoti Bhogal, Samantha Wittke at EPCC, Bayes Center, University of Edinburgh against the backdrop of the Holyrood Park (Salisbury Crags on the left, Arthur’s Seat on the right). Image credit: Catherine Inglis." srcset="
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-05-27_epcc_talk/bayes_center_holyrood_park_hu6226188194357269549.webp 400w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-05-27_epcc_talk/bayes_center_holyrood_park_hu5920640209434281563.webp 760w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-05-27_epcc_talk/bayes_center_holyrood_park_hu13504879025344997513.webp 1200w"
src="https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-05-27_epcc_talk/bayes_center_holyrood_park_hu6226188194357269549.webp"
width="760"
height="351"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/p>
&lt;p>On the day, &lt;strong>Catherine Inglis&lt;/strong> and &lt;strong>Neil Chue Hong&lt;/strong> welcomed us to the &lt;a href="https://bayes-centre.ed.ac.uk/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Bayes Centre at EPCC&lt;/a>. The robots on the ground floor of the Bayes Centre are hard to miss, and I must say, I was captivated by them! We all went on a tour of the EPCC building and met several members of the team there. Later, we stepped out and had a lunch break in the beautiful and sunny campus of the University of Edinburgh. It was during the chats with Catherine and Neil, I got to know that the Unicorn 🦄 - an imaginary creature - is the National Animal of Scotland, and then it made sense to me why the buildings in Edinburgh have so many unicorn statues!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="Image: (Left to Right) A robot at the Bayes Center, University of Edinburgh; The Unicron, the National Animal of Scotland" srcset="
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-05-27_epcc_talk/robot_unicorn_hu14053791878051609495.webp 400w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-05-27_epcc_talk/robot_unicorn_hu1885357626098156738.webp 760w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-05-27_epcc_talk/robot_unicorn_hu2764780780526347097.webp 1200w"
src="https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-05-27_epcc_talk/robot_unicorn_hu14053791878051609495.webp"
width="760"
height="562"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/p>
&lt;p>There were two talks planned for the day. The first one was by Samantha, who shared about the &lt;a href="https://coderefinery.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">CodeRefinery&lt;/a> project and her work with the &lt;a href="https://nordic-rse.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Nordic RSE&lt;/a>. Later, I presented my talk on the ongoing ‘Research Study on the Research Software Engineering (RSEng) Landscape in Asia’. Coincidentally, there were a few common points touched during both the talks - maybe CodeRefinery and RSE Asia could collaborate more closely in the future, but for now, I will focus this blog on my talk! 😊&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="Image: Jyoti Bhogal speaking about her “Research Study on the Research Software Engineering (RSEng) Landscape in Asia” at EPCC, Bayes Center, University of Edinburgh." srcset="
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-05-27_epcc_talk/epcc_jyoti_talk_title_slide_hu13862556047850879380.webp 400w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-05-27_epcc_talk/epcc_jyoti_talk_title_slide_hu18395822772695636408.webp 760w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-05-27_epcc_talk/epcc_jyoti_talk_title_slide_hu9049008084742139433.webp 1200w"
src="https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-05-27_epcc_talk/epcc_jyoti_talk_title_slide_hu13862556047850879380.webp"
width="760"
height="493"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="what-is-rse-asia">What is RSE Asia?&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>We (I and my co-Founder &lt;strong>Saranjeet Kaur&lt;/strong>) launched the &lt;a href="https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Research Software Engineering Asia Association (RSE Asia)&lt;/a> back in 2021, on the &lt;a href="https://researchsoftware.org/council/intl-rse-day.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">very first International RSE Day&lt;/a>, as there was almost no awareness about Research Software Engineering in the Asian region. Over the past 3+ years we have conducted and participated in various events and workshops to raise awareness about the profession and the community. Based on the reflections over this period, I started to explore the RSE landscape in the Asian region to get better informed insights.&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="what-is-my-project-about">What is my project about?&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>The motivation for this project was gained after reflecting over several of the community initiatives and interactions that RSE Asia had with the community in the region. I was further encouraged to take this work ahead when I proposed the idea during my talk on ‘&lt;a href="https://jyoti-bhogal.github.io/about-me/talks/2025-03-30_apan58/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">What is Research Software and Why Should we Think About its Sustainability?&lt;/a>’ at the 58th meeting of the Asia Pacific Advanced Network (APAN58) during August 2024, which was attended by delegates from across Asia Pacific as well as the globe. I have been developing this idea since then, and have been encouraged and supported to do so by several RSE community members, SSI fellows, and community leaders.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Speaking of why this study is required - this study is essential for several reasons, some of which are the need to diversify and expand the research software landscape, attempt to address the lack of formal RSE roles in Asia, leverage international partnerships, and further build a supportive community within Asia.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>SSI has been conducting surveys to study the RSE landscape since 2018. However, there has been almost no representation of Asia in these surveys. This makes my research study even more essential.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="Image: RSEs in the world in 2018, originally shared in the blog What do we know about RSEs? Results from our international surveys." srcset="
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-05-27_epcc_talk/ssi_survery_map_hu15950245902033643575.webp 400w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-05-27_epcc_talk/ssi_survery_map_hu11096678663734903656.webp 760w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-05-27_epcc_talk/ssi_survery_map_hu672506643558864757.webp 1200w"
src="https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-05-27_epcc_talk/ssi_survery_map_hu15950245902033643575.webp"
width="760"
height="375"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Within Asia, the Asia-Pacific Advanced Network (APAN) is an organisation that represents member institutions as well as it is a backbone network connecting member countries and regions to each other and to other international research and education networks. I am a member of APAN’s &lt;a href="https://apan.net/elements/working-groups/open-sharing-data/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Open and Sharing Data Working Group (OSDWG)&lt;/a>. This working group engages in dialogue and activities to promote good open science practices within research roles/institutes in the Asia Pacific. RSE Asia has had a consistent voice and representation during the biannual APAN meetings as a part of this working group. Through these engagements we realised the common interests we share with the working group and their intentions to help support the objectives of RSE Asia. Asia being a very complex and diverse region both, culturally and economically, it is essential to have the support from an established working group like the APAN’s OSDWG so as to have a better understanding of the research software landscape in the region.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="Image: APAN Current Members (as of December 2024). Source of information for creating map: APAN website." srcset="
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-05-27_epcc_talk/apan_current_members_hu16407296222288056876.webp 400w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-05-27_epcc_talk/apan_current_members_hu4347439335617471336.webp 760w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-05-27_epcc_talk/apan_current_members_hu4429776868388002966.webp 1200w"
src="https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-05-27_epcc_talk/apan_current_members_hu16407296222288056876.webp"
width="760"
height="485"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/p>
&lt;p>So far in this project, I have been able to refine and adapt the existing SSI surveys to make them suitable for the Asian context. I have also launched a pilot survey with a small group in APAN’s OSDWG to gain first-hand feedback on the survey so far. Next, I plan to refine the survey further based on this feedback before launching the full survey to a larger group. If you are either a researcher based in Asia or have worked in the Asian region or collaborate with colleagues in Asia, then please watch the &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/company/rse-asia-association/?viewAsMember=true" target="_blank" rel="noopener">RSE Asia page&lt;/a> for updates about my project and the survey - I would love to hear from you!&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="-concluding-the-day">🎉 Concluding the day&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>After the talks, we spent some time discussing our work with the audience, which smoothly transitioned into EPCC’s ritual of ‘Friday Buns’. We discussed the challenges and way forward. Later that evening, I walked up the Calton hill (recommended by many) and got to see a 360° view of the city, the valleys, as well as the beautiful North Sea. Being a bright, sunny day, with the sun setting almost post 10 pm, I went for a walk to the Portobello Beach, and loved every bit of it!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="Image (Left to Right): Me against the backdrop of the National Monument of Scotland on the Calton Hill; The beautiful blues and browns of the Portobello Beach in Edinburgh." srcset="
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-05-27_epcc_talk/edinburgh_nature_hu3289953717683451112.webp 400w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-05-27_epcc_talk/edinburgh_nature_hu18377849314722569752.webp 760w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-05-27_epcc_talk/edinburgh_nature_hu14326735887658741747.webp 1200w"
src="https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-05-27_epcc_talk/edinburgh_nature_hu3289953717683451112.webp"
width="760"
height="365"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I sincerely want to thank &lt;strong>Neil Chue Hong&lt;/strong> for inviting me to EPCC and to &lt;strong>Catherine Inglis&lt;/strong> for all the hospitality she offered. Last but definitely not least, a big thanks to &lt;strong>Sohail Sukhiani&lt;/strong> and &lt;strong>Oscar Seip&lt;/strong> for offering me a lot of behind-the-scenes support. I immensely value this opportunity of personal and professional growth!&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="-resources">🔑 Resources:&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Talk slides:&lt;/strong> &lt;a href="https://zenodo.org/records/15450346" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://zenodo.org/records/15450346&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h3 id="learn-more-about-us">&lt;strong>Learn More About Us&lt;/strong>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>For more information and to join upcoming events, visit:&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="rse-asia">RSE Asia&lt;/h4>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Website: &lt;a href="https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>For the latest news, events, activities, and opportunities, follow us on our &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/company/rse-asia-association/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">LinkedIn page&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>To join the RSE Asia community, please fill out our short &lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/forms/d/1XSxDaTJzcNyGeDYXyJNVg1TDCo7un18PLFNiK6_jL2g/edit" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Community Membership Form&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul></description></item><item><title>FOSSASIA Summit 2025</title><link>https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/</link><pubDate>Thu, 10 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/</guid><description>&lt;p>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="Wat Arun Ratchawararam Ratchawaramahawihan (Wat Arun temple), Bangkok, Thailand." srcset="
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/preview_wat_arun_hu4395619707160518832.webp 400w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/preview_wat_arun_hu12870335760176420076.webp 760w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/preview_wat_arun_hu4883880939432868856.webp 1200w"
src="https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/preview_wat_arun_hu4395619707160518832.webp"
width="760"
height="407"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>&lt;strong>Swa-dee-kah Bangkok! 👋🙏&lt;/strong>&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="-what-is-foss">🧑‍💻 What is FOSS?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>FOSS, an acronym for Free and Open Source Software, embodies a software development philosophy centered on freedom and openness. The term &amp;lsquo;Free&amp;rsquo; denotes users&amp;rsquo; liberty to run, alter, and share the software, while &amp;lsquo;Open Source&amp;rsquo; signifies that the software&amp;rsquo;s source code is available for users to inspect, modify, and contribute to its progress. FOSS promotes collaboration, transparency, and user empowerment. This frequently leads to the creation of more secure and sustainable software projects. Notable examples of FOSS include Linux, Blender, Chromium, Kubernetes, and Mozilla Firefox, among many more.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="-what-is-fossasia">🧑‍💻🌏 What is FOSSASIA?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://fossasia.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">FOSSASIA&lt;/a> is an organisation developing Open Source software applications and Open Hardware together with a global community from its base in Asia. Their goal is to provide access to open technologies, science applications and knowledge that improve people&amp;rsquo;s lives. They enable people to adapt and change technology according to their own ideas and needs, and validate science and knowledge through an Open Access approach. It was established in 2009 by &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/hongphucdang/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Hong Phuc Dang&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/mariobehling/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Mario Behling&lt;/a>. They organise and participate in conferences, meetups and code camps. The annual FOSSASIA Summit is one of the top tech events in Asia. FOSSASIA also runs a number of coding programs, such as &lt;a href="https://codeheat.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Codeheat&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The &lt;a href="https://eventyay.com/e/4c0e0c27" target="_blank" rel="noopener">15th edition of FOSSASIA Summit&lt;/a> was organised at True Digital Park, Bangkok, Thailand from 13th to 15th March 2025. It brought together individuals sharing talks on topics around Free and Open Source Software. The Summit had multiple parallel track sessions like talks, lightning talks, workshops, and more! There were booths by various organisations creating and/or using Free and Open Source Software. This was my first experience of attending FOSSASIA in-person in Thailand.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="-day-1">🗓️ Day 1&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The day started with a lot of fervour. Following the welcome session by Hong Phuc Dang, there were multiple parallel tracks of talks. One of the booths demonstrated &lt;em>&lt;strong>Robot Jupiter&lt;/strong>&lt;/em> (image below) - an interactive virtual education assistant!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="Robot Jupiter, virtual education assistant" srcset="
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/jupiter_robot_educational_assistant_hu13794346810542124047.webp 400w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/jupiter_robot_educational_assistant_hu596505261004575245.webp 760w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/jupiter_robot_educational_assistant_hu10152196276004389370.webp 1200w"
src="https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/jupiter_robot_educational_assistant_hu13794346810542124047.webp"
width="553"
height="760"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I had a chance to speak to Nancy Reyes, a representative from the &lt;a href="https://www.a11ylab.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">A11y Accessibility Labs&lt;/a>. She was showcasing the hardware items that they use for digital accessibility awareness training during their Usability and Accessibility Clinic sessions.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="Hardware items for digital accessibility awareness training" srcset="
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/hardware_and_software_accessibility_hu2981789961161384236.webp 400w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/hardware_and_software_accessibility_hu9049655007414283981.webp 760w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/hardware_and_software_accessibility_hu7704078689759508196.webp 1200w"
src="https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/hardware_and_software_accessibility_hu2981789961161384236.webp"
width="760"
height="365"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="A picture with Nancy Reyes from the A11y Accessibility Labs" srcset="
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/rse_asia_hu18357443411752010818.webp 400w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/rse_asia_hu6255961377230065161.webp 760w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/rse_asia_hu764290853054273577.webp 1200w"
src="https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/rse_asia_hu18357443411752010818.webp"
width="288"
height="216"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;em>A picture with &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/nancyreyesfl/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Nancy Reyes&lt;/a>, from the &lt;a href="https://www.a11ylab.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">A11y Accessibility Labs&lt;/a>, speaking about the mission of the RSE Asia Association.&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="-day-2">🗓️ Day 2&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="Me against the backdrop of the live LED screens at the conference venue True Digital Park." srcset="
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/jyoti_bhogal_true_digital_park_hu9211724051775702194.webp 400w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/jyoti_bhogal_true_digital_park_hu6454441547086564381.webp 760w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/jyoti_bhogal_true_digital_park_hu6852337217411483051.webp 1200w"
src="https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/jyoti_bhogal_true_digital_park_hu9211724051775702194.webp"
width="570"
height="760"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The second day of the summit, 14th March, was themed as PGDay 2025, a 1-day event focused on the PostgreSQL database, which was held in conjunction with the FOSSASIA Summit. I learnt about a new tool - &lt;a href="https://pgroll.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">pgroll&lt;/a>. It is an open-source command-line tool designed for PostgreSQL, ensuring that schema updates are applied safely, without locking the database, and enabling multiple schema versions to coexist. This ensures uninterrupted operation for client applications during migration, even when introducing breaking changes. The tool’s capability to automatically backfill columns and support instant rollbacks further enhances its reliability.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Later that day, I came across the booth of &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/company/grafana-labs/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Grafana Labs&lt;/a>. As I spoke to &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/richih/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Richard Hartmann&lt;/a>, he shared about the useful features of Grafana Labs tools for creating reports, metrics, and graphs about the code being written.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="-day-3">🗓️ Day 3&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>I held a ‘&lt;em>&lt;strong>Meet &amp;amp; Greet Spot&lt;/strong>&lt;/em>’ to speak to people about the field of Research Software Engineering, and discussed how it is a career path where one can combine their interest in implementing their research skills along with programming skills. I also shared about the past and the upcoming activities of the &lt;a href="https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Research Software Engineering (RSE) Asia Association&lt;/a>. Most people were curious to learn more about it, and also expressed a desire to join the future events held for the community.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="At the conference venue entrance door" srcset="
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/jyoti_bhogal_fossasia_summit_2025_poster_hu11164068731775730425.webp 400w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/jyoti_bhogal_fossasia_summit_2025_poster_hu17398043740992248417.webp 760w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/jyoti_bhogal_fossasia_summit_2025_poster_hu6485354994626380674.webp 1200w"
src="https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/jyoti_bhogal_fossasia_summit_2025_poster_hu11164068731775730425.webp"
width="760"
height="570"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="-cultural-warmth">👥 Cultural Warmth&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>From the moment I arrived at the Suvarnabhumi airport, I found everyone to be warm and welcoming. People at help desks, metro ticket counters, and even local markets were kind and helped me get around the city easily. I also learned something new about Thailand — it&amp;rsquo;s a pedestrian-first country, where vehicles stop to let people cross the road. Another thing I noticed was a good gender balance in the different workplaces that I came across.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="Depiction of Samudra Manthan (The Churning of the Ocean Milk), Suvarnabhumi Airport" srcset="
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/churning_ocean_milk_suvarnabhumi_airport_hu4853565785052944587.webp 400w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/churning_ocean_milk_suvarnabhumi_airport_hu6168598445551651087.webp 760w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/churning_ocean_milk_suvarnabhumi_airport_hu11578171994200421043.webp 1200w"
src="https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/churning_ocean_milk_suvarnabhumi_airport_hu4853565785052944587.webp"
width="760"
height="570"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/p>
&lt;p>With fresh fruits like mangoes, jackfruits, bananas, guavas, cashews, and coconuts, I truly experienced the tropical feel of the country. I enjoyed trying different types of bread, like red bean and almond bread. I also got to taste authentic Pad Thai noodles and Veg Thai Curry at a restaurant in True Digital Park. A fellow participant at the conference even taught me how to use chopsticks practically. I found Bangkok’s infrastructure very supportive for growth, with great workspaces and plenty of learning resources to help you make your own impact. Everyone I met — from the conference team to the hotel staff — was friendly and helpful, making the city feel not just a hub to flourish businesses and communities, but a place that warmly welcomes you again and again.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Here’s a glimpse of Bangkok through my eyes!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="Pad Thai noodles and vegetarian Thai curry at the Ginger Farm restaurant, True Digital Park" srcset="
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/pad_thai_noodles_hu255893316726781715.webp 400w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/pad_thai_noodles_hu3977903085000017417.webp 760w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/pad_thai_noodles_hu14899025521790407705.webp 1200w"
src="https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/pad_thai_noodles_hu255893316726781715.webp"
width="760"
height="570"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="The Great Bodhi Tree at the Wat Arun Ratchawararam Ratchawaramahawihan (Wat Arun temple), Bangkok, Thailand" srcset="
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/wat_arun_bodhi_tree_hu15311312930013773606.webp 400w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/wat_arun_bodhi_tree_hu5216849017775580175.webp 760w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/wat_arun_bodhi_tree_hu9074338275543790205.webp 1200w"
src="https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/wat_arun_bodhi_tree_hu15311312930013773606.webp"
width="760"
height="570"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="Night view of the Wat Arun Ratchawararam Ratchawaramahawihan (Wat Arun temple), Bangkok, Thailand" srcset="
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/wat_arun_night_view_hu17000656014442621381.webp 400w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/wat_arun_night_view_hu10811269505631675359.webp 760w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/wat_arun_night_view_hu11174394000620591023.webp 1200w"
src="https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/wat_arun_night_view_hu17000656014442621381.webp"
width="760"
height="570"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="Wat Pho, also known as the Temple of the Reclining Buddha" srcset="
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/wat_pho_temple_2_hu7248716128776745831.webp 400w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/wat_pho_temple_2_hu6475442039930818039.webp 760w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/wat_pho_temple_2_hu6707752146234198869.webp 1200w"
src="https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/wat_pho_temple_2_hu7248716128776745831.webp"
width="760"
height="570"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="Wat Pho, also known as the Temple of the Reclining Buddha" srcset="
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/wat_pho_temple_3_hu5642525036103178549.webp 400w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/wat_pho_temple_3_hu4898327453772873588.webp 760w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/wat_pho_temple_3_hu7697316060564706644.webp 1200w"
src="https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/wat_pho_temple_3_hu5642525036103178549.webp"
width="760"
height="570"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="-my-takeaway-">📕 My takeaway …&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>FOSSASIA Summit 2025 was especially close to my heart because it rekindled in me the spirit, zeal, and dedication towards contributing back to the software that we, knowingly or unknowingly, use on a day-to-day basis. As I left Thailand to return home, I carried so many learnings with me - especially the power that the voice of a community has!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>With that, I am concluding this blog until next time …&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="Wat Pho, also known as the Temple of the Reclining Buddha" srcset="
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/wat_pho_temple_1_hu7358190283318141940.webp 400w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/wat_pho_temple_1_hu6465378563647337677.webp 760w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/wat_pho_temple_1_hu12817486395345895593.webp 1200w"
src="https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-04-05_fossasia_summit_2025/wat_pho_temple_1_hu7358190283318141940.webp"
width="760"
height="570"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h3 id="learn-more-about-us">&lt;strong>Learn More About Us&lt;/strong>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>For more information and to join upcoming events, visit:&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="rse-asia">RSE Asia&lt;/h4>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Website: &lt;a href="https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>For the latest news, events, activities, and opportunities, follow us on our &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/company/rse-asia-association/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">LinkedIn page&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>To join the RSE Asia community, please fill out our short &lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/forms/d/1XSxDaTJzcNyGeDYXyJNVg1TDCo7un18PLFNiK6_jL2g/edit" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Community Membership Form&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul></description></item><item><title>Research, Software, and Collaborations</title><link>https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-03-30_apan58_apan59_blog/</link><pubDate>Thu, 10 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-03-30_apan58_apan59_blog/</guid><description>&lt;p>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="Mount Fuji, Japan. Photo by David Edelstein on Unsplash" srcset="
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-03-30_apan58_apan59_blog/david-edelstein-N4DbvTUDikw-unsplash_hu18157301937796507309.webp 400w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-03-30_apan58_apan59_blog/david-edelstein-N4DbvTUDikw-unsplash_hu2469300309647533437.webp 760w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-03-30_apan58_apan59_blog/david-edelstein-N4DbvTUDikw-unsplash_hu9811291813246369947.webp 1200w"
src="https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-03-30_apan58_apan59_blog/david-edelstein-N4DbvTUDikw-unsplash_hu18157301937796507309.webp"
width="580"
height="388"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>What is the Asia-Pacific Advanced Network (APAN)?&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>APAN is the international partnership of the National Research and Education Networks (NRENs) across the Asia Pacific region. It spans over half of the world’s population, and its members are fundamental in the provision of high-speed network connectivity domestically and globally.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>APAN has a number of working groups, one of which is the Open and Sharing Data Working Group (OSDWG). I became a member of this working group based on the common interest around developing the research software community and its importance in the research ecosystem.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>APAN organises biannual meetings bringing together its members and other interested participants to review progress, demonstrate advances in technology and applications, and make plans for the future activities in the Asia Pacific. Over the past months, I got the chance to attend APAN58 and APAN59 meetings, online remotely and exchange knowledge with its stakeholders. In this blog, I am capturing my experiences of attending these meetings.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="APAN58 Presentation Image" srcset="
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-03-30_apan58_apan59_blog/APAN58_talk_image_1_software_sustainability_methods_hu12679255357699436917.webp 400w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-03-30_apan58_apan59_blog/APAN58_talk_image_1_software_sustainability_methods_hu1880345936431998876.webp 760w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-03-30_apan58_apan59_blog/APAN58_talk_image_1_software_sustainability_methods_hu2976238838862877632.webp 1200w"
src="https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-03-30_apan58_apan59_blog/APAN58_talk_image_1_software_sustainability_methods_hu12679255357699436917.webp"
width="760"
height="347"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Source:&lt;/em> &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=giTd8lN88KQ" target="_blank" rel="noopener">APAN58 : Asia Pacific Open and Sharing Data WG, 27th August 2024, Part 1&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>During the APAN58 meeting (August 2024), I had the opportunity to present my talk titled &lt;em>&lt;strong>‘What is Research Software and Why Should we Think About its Sustainability?’&lt;/strong>&lt;/em> as part of the Open and Sharing Data Working Group (OSDWG) discussion session. Through my talk, I highlighted the importance of Research Software in the research ecosystem, explaining why it is necessary to think about its sustainability. I shared methods, tools, and best practices that can be utilised to improve the sustainability of research software, following up with the need and the benefits to include techniques for reproducibility in Research Software. Furthermore, I shared what software tools can be used to create, maintain, and share research software (Zenodo, GitHub, GitLab). I spoke about the different types of licenses that can be attached to the outputs of the research. This was followed by a summary of the journey of the &lt;a href="https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Research Software Engineering (RSE) Asia Association&lt;/a>, which I co-founded and co-lead since its launch in 2021.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>🔑 &lt;strong>Talk Resources:&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>Slides: Jyoti Bhogal. (2024, August 27). What is Research Software and Why Should we Think About its Sustainability?. Zenodo.&lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.13377699" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.13377699&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Recording: &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=giTd8lN88KQ" target="_blank" rel="noopener">APAN58 : Asia Pacific Open and Sharing Data WG, 27th August 2024, Part 1&lt;/a> (Clip from 00:00 to 14:55)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/giTd8lN88KQ?si=7P9Tu7Kj90rscXgm&amp;amp;start=1" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen>&lt;/iframe>
&lt;p>As I spoke about research software, its definition, the tools to write and maintain it, the audience became curious to know more about research software and the community around it. For the OSDWG session, which focused on topics like Open Science and how research software complements it, my presentation actually gave a keynote kind of a head start to the rest of the talks being presented in the session of OSDWG.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="APAN58 Presentation Task" srcset="
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-03-30_apan58_apan59_blog/APAN58_talk_image_2_task_hu11503873997529272157.webp 400w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-03-30_apan58_apan59_blog/APAN58_talk_image_2_task_hu17643718055601053226.webp 760w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-03-30_apan58_apan59_blog/APAN58_talk_image_2_task_hu9113764437418880555.webp 1200w"
src="https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-03-30_apan58_apan59_blog/APAN58_talk_image_2_task_hu11503873997529272157.webp"
width="760"
height="341"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;em>Source&lt;/em>: &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=giTd8lN88KQ" target="_blank" rel="noopener">APAN58 : Asia Pacific Open and Sharing Data WG, 27th August 2024, Part 1&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Towards the end of my talk, I asked the audience to share their feedback to the questions ‘What do you think about research software engineering as a role and as a career path?’ and ‘What are your thoughts on how open science might help the researchers worldwide?’ and received some interesting responses:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>“Looks interesting, since I have heard about it for the very first time in this talk at APAN58 meeting.”&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>“It is necessary for research software engineering management. I’ve heard that the organisations usually do not have enough capacity for managing research software engineers. However, they need software consistently. So, the public sectors help with this.”&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>“It&amp;rsquo;s an innovative way to share research, data and publications, etc.”&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>“So many students in the world have a very different situation in their social and life environment. For them, the internet and open science involving open access, open data, open software, and so on will help provide an education and research environment for equality.”&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>It was nice to see that my talk sparked curiosity in the audience and they promptly provided their feedback of what resonated with them. I also attended sessions on various topics including cybersecurity, high-performance computing &amp;amp; AI, agriculture and rural hybridization, network technologies, telemedicine and research collaborations. These sessions gave me more insights into the latest proceedings in the various fields of research and development in the Asia Pacific region.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In March 2025, I had the opportunity to speak at the &lt;strong>Asia Pacific Advanced Network’s APAN59 meeting&lt;/strong> online remotely. My presentation was on the title &lt;em>&lt;strong>‘Building Bridges: Advancing Research Software Engineering and Open Science in Asia’&lt;/strong>&lt;/em>. I gave my talk as part of the APAN’s Open and Sharing Data Working Group (OSDWG). Software being one of the pillars of Open Science, through this talk, I highlighted how paying attention towards developing and maintaining research software is directly linked to the principles of Open Science.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Later in March 2025, I had the opportunity to present my talk titled &lt;em>&lt;strong>‘Building Bridges: Advancing Research Software Engineering and Open Science in Asia’&lt;/strong>&lt;/em> at &lt;strong>APAN59,&lt;/strong> online remotely again as part of the OSDWG discussion session. Software being one of the pillars of Open Science, through this talk, I highlighted how paying attention towards developing and maintaining research software is directly linked to the principles of Open Science.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>During my talk, I shared about my ongoing &lt;strong>Research Study on the Research Software Engineering (RSEng) Landscape in Asia&lt;/strong>. I discussed the need of this study - due to the &lt;strong>no/low representation of the community of researchers who code in the Asian region&lt;/strong>. This is demonstrated by the outcomes of an existing global survey by the Software Sustainability Institute, which completely lacks representation from Asia.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="SSI Survey Summary Table" srcset="
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-03-30_apan58_apan59_blog/ssi_survey_summary_table_hu14328662006185527097.webp 400w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-03-30_apan58_apan59_blog/ssi_survey_summary_table_hu12058655987869181435.webp 760w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-03-30_apan58_apan59_blog/ssi_survey_summary_table_hu17883893208372967848.webp 1200w"
src="https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-03-30_apan58_apan59_blog/ssi_survey_summary_table_hu14328662006185527097.webp"
width="760"
height="564"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Source: Article by SSI: &lt;a href="https://www.software.ac.uk/blog/what-do-we-know-about-rses-results-our-international-surveys" target="_blank" rel="noopener">What do we know about RSEs? Results from our international surveys&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="SSI Survey Map" srcset="
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-03-30_apan58_apan59_blog/ssi_survey_map_hu15950245902033643575.webp 400w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-03-30_apan58_apan59_blog/ssi_survey_map_hu11096678663734903656.webp 760w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-03-30_apan58_apan59_blog/ssi_survey_map_hu672506643558864757.webp 1200w"
src="https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/RSE_Asia/blog/2025-03-30_apan58_apan59_blog/ssi_survey_map_hu15950245902033643575.webp"
width="760"
height="375"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Source: Article by SSI: &lt;a href="https://www.software.ac.uk/blog/what-do-we-know-about-rses-results-our-international-surveys" target="_blank" rel="noopener">What do we know about RSEs? Results from our international surveys&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I shared the roadmap of my research study with the audience. At the end of my talk, there were quite a few engaging questions. One of the comments from an active member of the APAN biannual meetings was&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>“The topic of this research study is something that deals with a national-level problem, thus making it much more essential to be studied.”&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>The appreciative feedback encourages me to keep taking my research work further.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>🔑 &lt;strong>Talk Resources:&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>Bhogal, J. (2025, March 3). Building Bridges: Advancing Research Software Engineering and Open Science in Asia. Zenodo. &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.15180196" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.15180196&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h3 id="learn-more-about-us">&lt;strong>Learn More About Us&lt;/strong>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>For more information and to join upcoming events, visit:&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="rse-asia">RSE Asia&lt;/h4>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Website: &lt;a href="https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>For the latest news, events, activities, and opportunities, follow us on our &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/company/rse-asia-association/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">LinkedIn page&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>To join the RSE Asia community, please fill out our short &lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/forms/d/1XSxDaTJzcNyGeDYXyJNVg1TDCo7un18PLFNiK6_jL2g/edit" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Community Membership Form&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul></description></item><item><title>Insights from My Experience at PyCon India 2024</title><link>https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/blog/2024-10-26_pycon_india_2024/</link><pubDate>Sat, 26 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/blog/2024-10-26_pycon_india_2024/</guid><description>&lt;p>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="Jyoti Bhogal with the PyCon India 2024 Banner" srcset="
/RSE_Asia/blog/2024-10-26_pycon_india_2024/cover_image_Jyoti_conf_banner_hu4533281636997668804.webp 400w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2024-10-26_pycon_india_2024/cover_image_Jyoti_conf_banner_hu17244280389917822082.webp 760w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2024-10-26_pycon_india_2024/cover_image_Jyoti_conf_banner_hu17295497999774588961.webp 1200w"
src="https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/RSE_Asia/blog/2024-10-26_pycon_india_2024/cover_image_Jyoti_conf_banner_hu4533281636997668804.webp"
width="760"
height="701"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="overview">Overview&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The PyCon India 2024 conference, held from September 20-23 at the NIMHANS Convention Center in Bengaluru, brought together a vibrant mix of sessions designed for learning, engagement, and networking. I experienced a diverse lineup, including keynotes, technical talks, hands-on workshops, lightning talks, poster sessions, and open forums (birds of feather (BoF) sessions). Sponsor stalls added to the excitement, and the open spaces allowed for spontaneous interactions, adding to the conference&amp;rsquo;s lively atmosphere. Celebrating its 15th anniversary this year, PyCon India 2024 marked my second time attending, following my first experience at PyCon India 2023 in Hyderabad.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="lightning-talks">Lightning Talks&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>I had the opportunity to present a Lightning Talk titled &lt;em>&amp;ldquo;Accelerating India&amp;rsquo;s Open Science Journey with Python.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em> In my session, I introduced the audience to the concept of open science, highlighting its importance for India, exploring its four foundational pillars, and demonstrating how Python plays a vital role in advancing open science efforts. The talk was well-received, and you can view the slides on &lt;a href="https://zenodo.org/records/13826028" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Zenodo&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="My Lightning Talk" srcset="
/RSE_Asia/blog/2024-10-26_pycon_india_2024/lightning_talk_collage_hu15859592698995382157.webp 400w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2024-10-26_pycon_india_2024/lightning_talk_collage_hu10090254969128491612.webp 760w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2024-10-26_pycon_india_2024/lightning_talk_collage_hu15857847507574625132.webp 1200w"
src="https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/RSE_Asia/blog/2024-10-26_pycon_india_2024/lightning_talk_collage_hu15859592698995382157.webp"
width="760"
height="361"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Click below to view video:&lt;/p>
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/lX896C6QUsE?si=3RwkwLRfNdqWATzb&amp;amp;start=1060" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen>&lt;/iframe>
&lt;h2 id="keynotes">Keynotes&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The conference featured four insightful keynotes:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://kovidgoyal.net/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Kovid Goyal&lt;/a> presented &lt;em>&amp;ldquo;Making Python Programs Fast,&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em> where he shared in-depth techniques to optimize Python performance using C language.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/usha-rengaraju-b570b7a2/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Usha Rengaraju&lt;/a> spoke on &lt;em>&amp;ldquo;AI for Autism,&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em> shedding light on neurodiversity and the potential of AI in autism research.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/mars-lee/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Mars Bar Lee&lt;/a> explored &lt;em>&amp;ldquo;How Open-Source Opened My Opportunities,&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em> highlighting how contributions to open-source projects can extend beyond code, such as her technical illustrations for NumPy.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/dontusethiscode/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">James Powell&lt;/a> delivered a creative talk, &lt;em>&amp;ldquo;How Many Oranges?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>Each keynote brought valuable perspectives, and Mars Bar Lee’s emphasis on non-code contributions was particularly interesting. I got to meet Mars in-person, after having met online previously for a workshop on importance of alt text with images for improving digital accessibility.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>
&lt;figure >
&lt;div class="d-flex justify-content-center">
&lt;div class="w-100" >&lt;img alt="L-R: Mars, Unicorn, me, and NumPy comics" srcset="
/RSE_Asia/blog/2024-10-26_pycon_india_2024/Mars_Jyoti_Unicorn_NumPy_Comics_hu7434170445446112914.webp 400w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2024-10-26_pycon_india_2024/Mars_Jyoti_Unicorn_NumPy_Comics_hu9277460117172359375.webp 760w,
/RSE_Asia/blog/2024-10-26_pycon_india_2024/Mars_Jyoti_Unicorn_NumPy_Comics_hu3108070987124473988.webp 1200w"
src="https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/RSE_Asia/blog/2024-10-26_pycon_india_2024/Mars_Jyoti_Unicorn_NumPy_Comics_hu7434170445446112914.webp"
width="760"
height="429"
loading="lazy" data-zoomable />&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>&lt;/figure>
&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="workshops">Workshops&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The first day had 3-hour workshops going on in three tracks. I attended two immersive workshops:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Chat with Tables: Developing Q&amp;amp;A system on Tabular data using Code Generative LLMs by &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/abhijeet-kumar-1aa8b0138/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Abhijeet Kumar&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Abhijeet conducted a workshop about Generative AI powered by Large Language Models (LLMs) that are revolutionizing text, image, and video generation, as well as coding through enterprise solutions like GitHub Copilot, Google’s Gemini Code Assist, IBM’s Watsonx, and Amazon’s Q Developer. Abhijeet&amp;rsquo;s workshop focused on leveraging code-generating LLMs to enable non-technical users to generate Python code by using natural language queries, bridging the gap for business users who lack programming skills but need quick data insights. This solution is valuable for business users who often require ad-hoc analysis of tabular data but rely heavily on data teams. Abhijeet demonstrated a workflow to query tabular data, generate insights from CSVs, and enhance natural language querying (NLQ) through techniques like few-shot prompting, pruning, and validation. Additionally, the session included setting up a streamlined process for building Q&amp;amp;A systems for tabular data and creating a Streamlit app, making data insights more accessible to non-technical analysts.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>From Zero to Backend Hero: Creating Full-Featured Apps with FastAPI by &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/vivek-keshore/?original_referer=https%3A%2F%2Fwww%2Egoogle%2Ecom%2F&amp;amp;originalSubdomain=in" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Vivek Keshore&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Vivek started by interacting with the audience to gather basic information like what an API is, the different types of APIs, and the various types of calls. Vivek discussed the benefits of using FastAPI. He went on to discuss database design. Vivek discussed about implementation of Pydantic models and the development of user management APIs.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;h2 id="pyladies-luncheon">PyLadies Luncheon&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The PyLadies Luncheon was a personal highlight during the conference. Women attendees gathered to share their experiences, openly discussing the challenges they face related to diversity and inclusivity in their workplaces and how they’ve overcome these obstacles over time. Hearing these stories and learning about the resilience and strategies of others was truly inspiring and energizing for me.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="sponsor-stalls">Sponsor Stalls&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The conference featured several sponsor stalls, and one that stood out to me was the &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/company/npci/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">National Payments Corporation of India (NPCI)&lt;/a>, an umbrella organization for retail payments and settlement systems in India. I was intrigued to learn how their payments ecosystem is entirely open-source, with data storage managed on-premises instead of on Cloud platforms. Additionally, they introduced me to UPI payments that can be made via phone call or SMS, allowing transactions without an internet connection.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="devsprints">DevSprints&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The DevSprint was a one-day event featuring around 20 different projects. The day began with core contributors providing an overview of their respective projects, allowing participants to choose any project they were interested in contributing to. Among the various projects, I found myself particularly drawn to Django and NumPy.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I opted to join the &lt;a href="https://github.com/numpy/numpy" target="_blank" rel="noopener">NumPy&lt;/a> DevSprint, facilitated by technical illustrator Mars Bar Lee and NumPy core contributor &lt;a href="https://github.com/seberg" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Sebastian Berg&lt;/a>. They introduced all the contributors to the NumPy project, outlining various ways to engage with the community through community calls, mailing lists, and comics, as well as how to contribute effectively. If you&amp;rsquo;re interested in contributing to NumPy, you can refer to the &lt;a href="https://github.com/numpy/numpy/blob/main/CONTRIBUTING.rst" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Contributing Guidelines&lt;/a> for more information.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I had the opportunity to attend an open session led by &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/saptaks/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Saptak S.&lt;/a>, where participants discussed the nuances of digital accessibility, particularly in website development. The discussion covered essential points such as ensuring adequate contrast between text and background colors, structuring headings (H1, H2, H3, etc.) correctly, and guidelines for including appropriate details in the alt text for images. I discovered several valuable online resources to check and test webpage accessibility, including:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.a11yproject.com/checklist/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">A11y Project&lt;/a>: A checklist for assessing accessibility levels.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.deque.com/axe/devtools/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">axe DevTools&lt;/a>: A tool that evaluates whether a website complies with accessibility guidelines, available as an extension for Chrome, Firefox, and MS Edge browsers.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://wave.webaim.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">WAVE&lt;/a>: A tool that highlights areas of a website that are well or poorly designed regarding accessibility. WAVE also offers extensions for Chrome, Firefox, and MS Edge browsers.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.buttoncheatsheet.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">The Button Cheat Sheet&lt;/a>: A resource to determine if buttons on a website&amp;rsquo;s UI are designed effectively.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://webaim.org/projects/million/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">The WebAIM Million&lt;/a>: The 2024 report on the accessibility of the top 1,000,000 home pages.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>We discussed key considerations for developers when creating digitally accessible web pages. For instance, keyboard navigation is crucial for individuals with visual impairments or otherwise while working with a document by using only the keyboard, necessitating a logical heading structure (e.g., H1 followed by H2, and so on). It’s important to avoid jumping from say, H1 to H4, as this can confuse users.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In terms of coding practices, developers should specify the document language by adding the ‘lang’ attribute. This helps indicate which programming language is being used for different sections of the website. Additionally, tools like &lt;a href="https://www.freedomscientific.com/products/software/jaws/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">JAWS&lt;/a> provide voice assistance to help developers ensure accessibility standards are met.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>During Continuous Integration (CI), it’s essential for developers to incorporate these accessibility guidelines into their workflows.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Saptak also recommended several excellent learning resources, such as &lt;a href="https://adrianroselli.com/tag/accessibility" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Adrian Roselli’s&lt;/a> articles on accessibility issues, conference talks from experts in digital accessibility, and a helpful site for determining whether to use a carousel post: &lt;a href="https://shouldiuseacarousel.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Should I Use a Carousel?&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The PyCon India 2024 concluded with the DevSprints, marking an incredibly immersive learning experience for me. The Closing Ceremony featured two beat-box artists who entertained us, adding a refreshing twist to the event. I also had the pleasure of meeting &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/tanvi-agarwal-sillystrokes/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Tanvi Agarwal&lt;/a>, a digital illustrator who provides live transcription of talks, which I found truly inspiring. A big thank you to the entire PyCon India volunteer organizing team for once again delivering a fantastic conference!&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h3 id="learn-more-about-us">&lt;strong>Learn More About Us&lt;/strong>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>For more information and to join upcoming events, visit:&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="rse-asia">RSE Asia&lt;/h4>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Website: &lt;a href="https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>For the latest news, events, activities, and opportunities, follow us on our &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/company/rse-asia-association/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">LinkedIn page&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>To join the RSE Asia community, please fill out our short &lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/forms/d/1XSxDaTJzcNyGeDYXyJNVg1TDCo7un18PLFNiK6_jL2g/edit" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Community Membership Form&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul></description></item><item><title>My Experience of Participating in Open Life Science Cohort-5</title><link>https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/blog/2022-10-07-ols5exp22/</link><pubDate>Wed, 10 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/blog/2022-10-07-ols5exp22/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>Click below for the slide.&lt;/em>
&lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1aYyBzvDkGMRzl1pMt0RJ4de772t-SwzGyXgmMkHrUWY/edit#slide=id.p" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1aYyBzvDkGMRzl1pMt0RJ4de772t-SwzGyXgmMkHrUWY/edit#slide=id.p&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;a href="`r rmarkdown::metadata$url`">
```{r}
knitr::include_graphics("preview.png")
```
&lt;/a>
&lt;h2 id="project-title-and-motivation">Project Title and Motivation&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>In the OLS-5 cohort, I got the opportunity to work on my project titled &amp;lsquo;Building Pathways for Onboarding to Research Software Engineering (RSE) Asia Association and Adoption of Code of Conduct&amp;rsquo;. My mentor for the program was &lt;a href="https://malvikasharan.github.io/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Malvika Sharan&lt;/a>. There are several incidents when people want to contribute in a community activity, but the community does not have a well-defined path that will help a new person contribute. This motivated me to work on building pathways for new members to join the RSE Asia Association.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="the-backstory">The Backstory&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The inception of RSE Asia Association goes back to September 2021, when our idea of starting it got the support of the experts from the OLS-4 cohort. Back then we started off with a basic logo. We had set up the entire digital structure need to run the community. During cohort 5, we updated the logo.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="milestones-the-rse-asia-association-crossed-during-ols-5">Milestones the RSE Asia Association Crossed During OLS-5&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Let&amp;rsquo;s have a look at the milestones in the journey that RSE Asia Association went through while OLS-5.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="milestone-1">Milestone 1&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The selection into OLS-5 itself was a milestone. Following which, we started discussions around how to get our Association registered.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We wanted to register ourselves as an NGO. With the guidance from my mentor Malvika, I read several articles. I found out about the different types of NGOs that function here in India. After careful reading, understanding and discussions with my mentor, we finalized which type of NGO would be best for us to register as. At the moment, the registration is a work in progress.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="milestone-2">Milestone 2&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>When it comes to community work, we had identified that a lot of people are enthusiastic about participating in community work, however many communities face an issue when it comes to a smooth process for people to join them. Hence, we decided to define clear pathways for people to join us, to contribute/learn for a specific time duration.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="milestone-3">Milestone 3&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The RSE Asia Association also got listed as an &amp;lsquo;Observer Association&amp;rsquo; at the International Council of RSE Associations.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="milestone-4">Milestone 4&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>On 8th July 2022, we conducted a workshop, where Isabela Presedo-Floyd and Mars Lee very graciously accepted our invitation to share their knowledge of how alt-texts are written. It was indeed a very exciting and engaging event where people did hands-on work!&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="next-steps">Next steps&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Jyoti would continue with the formalities of getting the association registered legally. Saranjeet and Jyoti are planning to conduct more and more exciting events and workshops.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="staying-connected">Staying connected&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Come have a look at our activities!
We are absolutely active on Twitter. We send out all our updates, reminders and links to various forms via our twitter handle which is @RSE_Asia. Do check out our twitter page, look at our past and upcoming events, DM us to speak your thoughts!&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="special-mentions-and-acknowledgements">Special mentions and acknowledgements&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>We feel very grateful to the OLS team for giving us this chance to grow our RSE Asia Association!
We are extremely thankful to be a part of such a wonderful and supportive community that OLS is!
And our contact details are shown herewith. You can get in touch with us via our twitter handle, our email address.
You can also visit our website, YouTube channel or our GitHub page.
Thank you!!!&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h3 id="learn-more-about-us">&lt;strong>Learn More About Us&lt;/strong>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>For more information and to join upcoming events, visit:&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="rse-asia">RSE Asia&lt;/h4>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Website: &lt;a href="https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://rse-asia.github.io/RSE_Asia/&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>For the latest news, events, activities, and opportunities, follow us on our &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/company/rse-asia-association/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">LinkedIn page&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>To join the RSE Asia community, please fill out our short &lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/forms/d/1XSxDaTJzcNyGeDYXyJNVg1TDCo7un18PLFNiK6_jL2g/edit" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Community Membership Form&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul></description></item></channel></rss>